<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science | Imad Dabbura</title>
    <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/categories/data-science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://imaddabbura.github.io/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Data Science</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Imad Dabbura 2018</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Data Science</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/categories/data-science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conda Essentials Notes</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/conda-essentials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/conda-essentials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 


  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/conda/conda.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/conda/conda.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
 --&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conda&lt;/strong&gt; in an open source package management system that works on all platforms. It is a tool that helps manage packages and environments for different programming languages. Develop a high level understanding of how Conda works helped me at so many levels especially when it comes to managing environments and make my work more reproducable. Below are the notes that I wrote down during my journey of learning Conda and I always refere back to them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
General&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conda packages are files and executables that can in principle contain images, data, noteboeeks, files, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conda mainly used in Python ecosystem; however, it can be used with other languages such R, Julia, Scala, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When installing a package using Conda, it installs its dependencies with it. Also, Conda is able to figure out the platform you&#39;re using without the need to specify the platform when installing packages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When installing a package, Conda:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checks the platform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checks the Python version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the latest version of the package that is compatible with Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it has dependencies, installs the latest versions of the dependencies that are also compatible with each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under semantic versioning, software is labeled with a three-part version identifier of the form &lt;code&gt;MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH&lt;/code&gt;; the label components are non-negative integers separated by periods. Assuming all software starts at version 0.0.0, the &lt;code&gt;MAJOR&lt;/code&gt; version number is increased when significant new functionality is introduced (often with corresponding API changes). Increases in the &lt;code&gt;MINOR&lt;/code&gt; version number generally reflect improvements (e.g., new features) that avoid backward-incompatible API changes. For instance, adding an optional argument to a function API (in a way that allows old code to run unchanged) is a change worthy of increasing the &lt;code&gt;MINOR&lt;/code&gt; version number. An increment to the &lt;code&gt;PATCH&lt;/code&gt; version number is approriate mostly for bug fixes that preserve the same &lt;code&gt;MAJOR&lt;/code&gt; and MINOR revision numbers. Software patches do not typically introduce new features or change APIs at all (except sometimes to address security issues).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can specify &lt;code&gt;MAJOR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MAJOR.MINOR&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH&lt;/code&gt; when installing any package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can use logical operators to install versions of a package. Examples:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda install &#39;python=3.6|3.7&#39;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda install &#39;python=3.6|3.7*&#39;&lt;/code&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda install &#39;python&amp;gt;=3.6, &amp;lt;=3.7&#39;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Common Commands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To update a package, &lt;code&gt;conda update pckg&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To uninstall a package, &lt;code&gt;conda remove pckg&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To search what available versions of a specific package is available, use &lt;code&gt;conda search pckg&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda list&lt;/code&gt; will list all installed packages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda list -n env-name&lt;/code&gt; will list all packages in the environment env-name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda list pckg&lt;/code&gt; will give information about pckg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When installing a pckg without including a channel, it defaults to the main channel that is maintained by Anaconda Inc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There other channels where people can upload their packages to and we can reach to those channels when looking for installation such fastai. We use &lt;code&gt;conda install -c fastai fastai&lt;/code&gt;. Here the channel is fastai and the pckg is also fastai.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;conda search -c conda-forge -c fastai --override-channels --platform osx-64 fastai&lt;/code&gt; means:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for fastai in two channels: conda-forge, fastai.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;override-channels means do not go to default main channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;platform specify which platform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes we don&#39;t know the channel of the pckg, we can use &lt;code&gt;anaconda search pckg&lt;/code&gt; that will return all the channels that the pckg is at and their versions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conda-forge is almost as good as the main channels which is led by the community. It has a lot more packages than the main channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no system that rates channels, so be carefel when installing packages from any channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can list all packages in a channel such as &lt;code&gt;conda search -c conda-forge --override-channels&lt;/code&gt; that will list all packages for the conda-forge channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Environments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environments are a good practice of documenting data science/software development work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environments are nothing more than a directory that contains all the packages so that when trying to import them, it imports them from this directory only. we can use &lt;code&gt;conda env list&lt;/code&gt; to see all the available environments on our machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the packages from a specific environment by name, use &lt;code&gt;conda list -n env-name&lt;/code&gt;. Otherwise, we get the packages from the current environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To activate an environment, use &lt;code&gt;conda activate env-name&lt;/code&gt;. To deactivate, &lt;code&gt;conda deactivate&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environments usually don&#39;t take a lot of space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can remove environments using &lt;code&gt;conda env remove -n env-name&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create an environment, use &lt;code&gt;conda create -n env-name&lt;/code&gt;. We can also add additional package names to install after creation such as &lt;code&gt;conda create -n env-name python=3.6* numpy&amp;gt;=1.1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To export an environment, use &lt;code&gt;conda env export -n env-name&lt;/code&gt;. This will return the output to the terminal. We can also export to a file. For that use &lt;code&gt;conda env export -n env-name -f env-name.yml&lt;/code&gt;. The &#39;.yml&#39; extension is strongly enouraged. Doing this will assure that all the packages used can be installed by others exactly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can create also an environment from .yml file using &lt;code&gt;conda env create -f env-name.yml&lt;/code&gt;. Note also that if we only use &lt;code&gt;conda env create&lt;/code&gt;, it will look for a file that has .yml extension and has the same name as env-name in the current local directory. Moreover, we can create the .yml file with doing the export ourselves and only specify what is important in our environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>K-means Clustering - Algorithm, Applications, Evaluation Methods, and Drawbacks</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/kmeans-clustering/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/kmeans-clustering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 


  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/kmeans.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/kmeans.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
 --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Clustering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#kmeans&#34;&gt;Kmeans Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#implementation&#34;&gt;Implementation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#application&#34;&gt;Applications&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2dexample&#34;&gt;Geyser&#39;s Eruptions Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#imagecompression&#34;&gt;Image Compression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#evaluation&#34;&gt;Evaluation Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#drawbacks&#34;&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;introduction&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Clustering
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clustering&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the most common exploratory data analysis technique used to get an intuition about the structure of the data. It can be defined as the task of identifying subgroups in the data such that data points in the same subgroup (cluster) are very similar while data points in different clusters are very different. In other words, we try to find homogeneous subgroups within the data such that data points in each cluster are as similar as possible according to a similarity measure such as euclidean-based distance or correlation-based distance. The decision of which similarity measure to use is application-specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clustering analysis can be done on the basis of features where we try to find subgroups of samples based on features or on the basis of samples where we try to find subgroups of features based on samples. We&#39;ll cover here clustering based on features. Clustering is used in market segmentation; where we try to fin  d customers that are similar to each other whether in terms of behaviors or attributes, image segmentation/compression; where we try to group similar regions together, document clustering based on topics, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike supervised learning, clustering is considered an unsupervised learning method since we don&#39;t have the ground truth to compare the output of the clustering algorithm to the true labels to evaluate its performance. We only want to try to investigate the structure of the data by grouping the data points into distinct subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will cover only &lt;strong&gt;Kmeans&lt;/strong&gt; which is considered as one of the most commonly used clustering algorithms due to its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;kmeans&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Kmeans Algorithm
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kmeans&lt;/strong&gt; algorithm is an iterative algorithm that tries to partition the dataset into &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; pre-defined distinct non-overlapping subgroups (clusters) where each data point belongs to &lt;strong&gt;only one group&lt;/strong&gt;. It tries to make the inter-cluster data points as similar as possible while also keeping
the clusters as different (far) as possible. It assigns data points to a cluster such that the sum of the squared distance between the data points and the cluster&#39;s centroid (arithmetic mean of all the data points that belong to that cluster) is at the minimum. The less variation we have within clusters, the more homogeneous (similar) the data points are within the same cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way kmeans algorithm works is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify number of clusters &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize centroids by first shuffling the dataset and then randomly selecting &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; data points for the centroids without replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep iterating until there is no change to the centroids. i.e assignment of data points to clusters isn&#39;t changing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the sum of the squared distance between data points and all centroids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign each data point to the closest cluster (centroid).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the centroids for the clusters by taking the average of all data points that belong to each cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach kmeans follows to solve the problem is called &lt;strong&gt;Expectation-Maximization&lt;/strong&gt;. The E-step is assigning the data points to the closest cluster. The M-step is computing the centroid of each cluster. Below is a break down of how we can solve it mathematically (feel free to skip it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective function is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[J = \sum_{i = 1}^{m}\sum_{k = 1}^{K}w_{ik}\|x^i - \mu_k\|^2\tag{1}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $w_{ik} = 1$ for data point $x^i$ if it belongs to cluster &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;; otherwise, $w_{ik} = 0$. Also, $\mu_k$ is the centroid of $x^i$&#39;s cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a minimization problem of two parts. We first minimize J w.r.t. $w_{ik}$ and treat $\mu_k$ fixed. Then we minimize J w.r.t. $\mu&lt;em&gt;k$ and treat $w&lt;/em&gt;{ik}$ fixed. Technically speaking, we differentiate J w.r.t. $w_{ik}$ first and update cluster assignments  (&lt;em&gt;E-step&lt;/em&gt;). Then we differentiate J w.r.t. $\mu_{k}$ and recompute the centroids after the cluster assignments from previous step  (&lt;em&gt;M-step&lt;/em&gt;). Therefore, E-step is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\frac{\partial J}{\partial w_{ik}} = \sum_{i = 1}^{m}\sum_{k = 1}^{K}\|x^i - \mu_k\|^2\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\Rightarrow \begin{equation} w_{ik} = \begin{cases} 1 &amp; \text{if $k = arg min_j\ \|x^i - \mu_j\|^2$} \\\\\\
0 &amp; \text{otherwise}. \end{cases} \end{equation}\tag{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;
In other words, assign the data point $x^i$ to the closest cluster judged by its sum of squared distance from cluster&#39;s centroid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And M-step is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\ \frac{\partial J}{\partial \mu_k} = 2\sum_{i = 1}^{m}w_{ik}(x^i - \mu_k) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\Rightarrow \mu_k = \frac{\sum_{i = 1}^{m}w_{ik}x^i}{\sum_{i = 1}^{m}w_{ik}}\tag{3}\)&lt;/span&gt;
Which translates to recomputing the centroid of each cluster to reflect the new assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few things to note here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since clustering algorithms including kmeans use distance-based measurements to determine the similarity between data points, it&#39;s recommended to standardize the data to have a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one since almost always the features in any dataset would have different units of measurements such as age vs income.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given kmeans iterative nature and the random initialization of centroids at the start of the algorithm, different initializations may lead to different clusters since kmeans algorithm may &lt;em&gt;stuck in a local optimum and may not converge to global optimum&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, it&#39;s recommended to run the algorithm using different initializations of centroids and pick the results of the run that that yielded the lower sum of squared distance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assignment of examples isn&#39;t changing is the same thing as no change in within-cluster variation:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[\frac{1}{m_k}\sum_{i = 1}^{m_k}\|x^i - \mu_{c^k}\|^2\tag{4}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;implementation&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Implementation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll use simple implementation of kmeans here to just illustrate some concepts. Then we will use &lt;code&gt;sklearn&lt;/code&gt; implementation that is more efficient take care of many things for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import numpy as np
from numpy.linalg import norm


class Kmeans:
    &#39;&#39;&#39;Implementing Kmeans algorithm.&#39;&#39;&#39;

    def __init__(self, n_clusters, max_iter=100, random_state=123):
        self.n_clusters = n_clusters
        self.max_iter = max_iter
        self.random_state = random_state

    def initializ_centroids(self, X):
        np.random.RandomState(self.random_state)
        random_idx = np.random.permutation(X.shape[0])
        centroids = X[random_idx[:self.n_clusters]]
        return centroids

    def compute_centroids(self, X, labels):
        centroids = np.zeros((self.n_clusters, X.shape[1]))
        for k in range(self.n_clusters):
            centroids[k, :] = np.mean(X[labels == k, :], axis=0)
        return centroids

    def compute_distance(self, X, centroids):
        distance = np.zeros((X.shape[0], self.n_clusters))
        for k in range(self.n_clusters):
            row_norm = norm(X - centroids[k, :], axis=1)
            distance[:, k] = np.square(row_norm)
        return distance

    def find_closest_cluster(self, distance):
        return np.argmin(distance, axis=1)

    def compute_sse(self, X, labels, centroids):
        distance = np.zeros(X.shape[0])
        for k in range(self.n_clusters):
            distance[labels == k] = norm(X[labels == k] - centroids[k], axis=1)
        return np.sum(np.square(distance))
    
    def fit(self, X):
        self.centroids = self.initializ_centroids(X)
        for i in range(self.max_iter):
            old_centroids = self.centroids
            distance = self.compute_distance(X, old_centroids)
            self.labels = self.find_closest_cluster(distance)
            self.centroids = self.compute_centroids(X, self.labels)
            if np.all(old_centroids == self.centroids):
                break
        self.error = self.compute_sse(X, self.labels, self.centroids)
    
    def predict(self, X):
        distance = self.compute_distance(X, self.centroids)
        return self.find_closest_cluster(distance)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;application&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Applications
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;kmeans algorithm is very popular and used in a variety of applications such as market segmentation, document clustering, image segmentation and image compression, etc. The goal usually when we undergo a cluster analysis is either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a meaningful intuition of the structure of the data we&#39;re dealing with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cluster-then-predict where different models will be built for different subgroups if we believe there is a wide variation in the behaviors of different subgroups. An example of that is clustering patients into different subgroups and build a model for each subgroup to predict the probability of the risk of having heart attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we&#39;ll apply clustering on two cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geyser eruptions segmentation (2-D dataset).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image compression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;2dexample&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Kmeans on Geyser&#39;s Eruptions Segmentation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll first implement the kmeans algorithm on 2D dataset and see how it works. The dataset has 272 observations and 2 features. The data covers the waiting time between eruptions and the duration of the eruption for the Old Faithful geyser in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, USA. We will try to find &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; subgroups within the data points and group them accordingly. Below is the description of the features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eruptions (float): Eruption time in minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;waiting (int):  Waiting time to next eruption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s plot the data first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Modules
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
from matplotlib.image import imread
import pandas as pd
import seaborn as sns
from sklearn.datasets.samples_generator import (make_blobs,
                                                make_circles,
                                                make_moons)
from sklearn.cluster import KMeans, SpectralClustering
from sklearn.preprocessing import StandardScaler
from sklearn.metrics import silhouette_samples, silhouette_score

%matplotlib inline
sns.set_context(&#39;notebook&#39;)
plt.style.use(&#39;fivethirtyeight&#39;)
from warnings import filterwarnings
filterwarnings(&#39;ignore&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Import the data
df = pd.read_csv(&#39;../data/old_faithful.csv&#39;)

# Plot the data
plt.figure(figsize=(6, 6))
plt.scatter(df.iloc[:, 0], df.iloc[:, 1])
plt.xlabel(&#39;Eruption time in mins&#39;)
plt.ylabel(&#39;Waiting time to next eruption&#39;)
plt.title(&#39;Visualization of raw data&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_raw.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_raw.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll use this data because it&#39;s easy to plot and visually spot the clusters since its a 2-dimension dataset. It&#39;s obvious that we have 2 clusters. Let&#39;s standardize the data first and run the kmeans algorithm on the standardized data with $K = 2$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Standardize the data
X_std = StandardScaler().fit_transform(df)

# Run local implementation of kmeans
km = Kmeans(n_clusters=2, max_iter=100)
km.fit(X_std)
centroids = km.centroids

# Plot the clustered data
fig, ax = plt.subplots(figsize=(6, 6))
plt.scatter(X_std[km.labels == 0, 0], X_std[km.labels == 0, 1],
            c=&#39;green&#39;, label=&#39;cluster 1&#39;)
plt.scatter(X_std[km.labels == 1, 0], X_std[km.labels == 1, 1],
            c=&#39;blue&#39;, label=&#39;cluster 2&#39;)
plt.scatter(centroids[:, 0], centroids[:, 1], marker=&#39;*&#39;, s=300,
            c=&#39;r&#39;, label=&#39;centroid&#39;)
plt.legend()
plt.xlim([-2, 2])
plt.ylim([-2, 2])
plt.xlabel(&#39;Eruption time in mins&#39;)
plt.ylabel(&#39;Waiting time to next eruption&#39;)
plt.title(&#39;Visualization of clustered data&#39;, fontweight=&#39;bold&#39;)
ax.set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_clustered.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_clustered.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above graph shows the scatter plot of the data colored by the cluster they belong to. In this example, we chose $K = 2$. The symbol &lt;strong&gt;&#39;*&#39;&lt;/strong&gt; is the centroid of each cluster. We can think of those 2 clusters as geyser had different kinds of behaviors under different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we&#39;ll show that different initializations of centroids may yield to different results. I&#39;ll use 9 different &lt;code&gt;random_state&lt;/code&gt; to change the initialization of the centroids and plot the results. The title of each plot will be the sum of squared distance of each initialization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, this dataset is considered very easy and converges in less than 10 iterations. Therefore, to see the effect of random initialization on convergence, I am going to go with 3 iterations to illustrate the concept. However, in real world applications, datasets are not at all that clean and nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;n_iter = 9
fig, ax = plt.subplots(3, 3, figsize=(16, 16))
ax = np.ravel(ax)
centers = []
for i in range(n_iter):
    # Run local implementation of kmeans
    km = Kmeans(n_clusters=2,
                max_iter=3,
                random_state=np.random.randint(0, 1000, size=1))
    km.fit(X_std)
    centroids = km.centroids
    centers.append(centroids)
    ax[i].scatter(X_std[km.labels == 0, 0], X_std[km.labels == 0, 1],
                  c=&#39;green&#39;, label=&#39;cluster 1&#39;)
    ax[i].scatter(X_std[km.labels == 1, 0], X_std[km.labels == 1, 1],
                  c=&#39;blue&#39;, label=&#39;cluster 2&#39;)
    ax[i].scatter(centroids[:, 0], centroids[:, 1],
                  c=&#39;r&#39;, marker=&#39;*&#39;, s=300, label=&#39;centroid&#39;)
    ax[i].set_xlim([-2, 2])
    ax[i].set_ylim([-2, 2])
    ax[i].legend(loc=&#39;lower right&#39;)
    ax[i].set_title(f&#39;{km.error:.4f}&#39;)
    ax[i].set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;)
plt.tight_layout();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_multiple.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/geyser_multiple.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the graph above shows that we only ended up with two different ways of clusterings based on different initializations. We would pick the one with the lowest sum of squared distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;imagecompression&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Kmeans on Image Compression
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part, we&#39;ll implement kmeans to compress an image. The image that we&#39;ll be working on is 396 x 396 x 3. Therefore, for each pixel location we would have 3 8-bit integers that specify the red, green, and blue intensity values. Our goal is to reduce the number of colors to 30 and represent (compress) the photo using those 30 colors only. To pick which colors to use, we&#39;ll use kmeans algorithm on the image and treat every pixel as a data point. That means reshape the image from height x width x channels to (height * width) x channel, i,e we would have 396 x 396 = 156,816 data points in 3-dimensional space which are the intensity of RGB. Doing so will allow us to represent the image using the 30 centroids for each pixel and would significantly reduce the size of the image by a factor of 6. The original image size was 396 x 396 x 24 = 3,763,584 bits; however, the new compressed image would be 30 x 24 + 396 x 396 x 4 = 627,984 bits. The huge difference comes from the fact that we&#39;ll be using centroids as a lookup for pixels&#39; colors and that would reduce the size of each pixel location to 4-bit instead of 8-bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now on we will be using &lt;code&gt;sklearn&lt;/code&gt; implementation of kmeans. Few thing to note here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;n_init&lt;/code&gt; is the number of times of running the kmeans with different centroid&#39;s initialization. The result of the best one will be reported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tol&lt;/code&gt; is the within-cluster variation metric used to declare convergence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The default of &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;k-means++&lt;/strong&gt; which is supposed to yield a better results than just random initialization of centroids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Read the image
img = imread(&#39;images/my_image.jpg&#39;)
img_size = img.shape

# Reshape it to be 2-dimension
X = img.reshape(img_size[0] * img_size[1], img_size[2])

# Run the Kmeans algorithm
km = KMeans(n_clusters=30)
km.fit(X)

# Use the centroids to compress the image
X_compressed = km.cluster_centers_[km.labels_]
X_compressed = np.clip(X_compressed.astype(&#39;uint8&#39;), 0, 255)

# Reshape X_recovered to have the same dimension as the original image 128 * 128 * 3
X_compressed = X_compressed.reshape(img_size[0], img_size[1], img_size[2])

# Plot the original and the compressed image next to each other
fig, ax = plt.subplots(1, 2, figsize = (12, 8))
ax[0].imshow(img)
ax[0].set_title(&#39;Original Image&#39;)
ax[1].imshow(X_compressed)
ax[1].set_title(&#39;Compressed Image with 30 colors&#39;)
for ax in fig.axes:
    ax.axis(&#39;off&#39;)
plt.tight_layout();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/image_compression.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/image_compression.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can see the comparison between the original image and the compressed one. The compressed image looks close to the original one which means we&#39;re able to retain the majority of the characteristics of the original image. With smaller number of clusters we would have higher compression rate at the expense of image quality. As a side note, this image compression method is called &lt;em&gt;lossy data compression&lt;/em&gt; because we can&#39;t reconstruct the original image from the compressed image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;evaluation&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Evaluation Methods
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to supervised learning where we have the ground truth to evaluate the model&#39;s performance, clustering analysis doesn&#39;t have a solid evaluation metric that we can use to evaluate the outcome of different clustering algorithms. Moreover, since kmeans requires &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; as an input and doesn&#39;t learn it from data, there is no right answer in terms of the number of clusters that we should have in any problem. Sometimes domain knowledge and intuition may help but usually that is not the case. In the cluster-predict methodology, we can evaluate how well the models are performing based on different &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; clusters since clusters are used in the downstream modeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we&#39;ll cover two metrics that may give us some intuition about &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elbow method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Silhouette analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;elbow&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Elbow Method
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Elbow&lt;/strong&gt; method gives us an idea on what a good &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; number of clusters would be based on the sum of squared distance (SSE) between data points and their assigned clusters&#39; centroids. We pick &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; at the spot where SSE starts to flatten out and forming an elbow. We&#39;ll use the geyser dataset and evaluate SSE for different values of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; and see where the curve might form an elbow and flatten out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Run the Kmeans algorithm and get the index of data points clusters
sse = []
list_k = list(range(1, 10))

for k in list_k:
    km = KMeans(n_clusters=k)
    km.fit(X_std)
    sse.append(km.inertia_)

# Plot sse against k
plt.figure(figsize=(6, 6))
plt.plot(list_k, sse, &#39;-o&#39;)
plt.xlabel(r&#39;Number of clusters *k*&#39;)
plt.ylabel(&#39;Sum of squared distance&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/elbow.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/elbow.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The graph above shows that $k = 2$ is not a bad choice. Sometimes it&#39;s still hard to figure out a good number of clusters to use because the curve is monotonically decreasing and may not show any elbow or has an obvious point where the curve starts flattening out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;silhouette&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Silhouette Analysis
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silhouette analysis&lt;/strong&gt; can be used to determine the degree of separation between clusters. For each sample:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the average distance from all data points in the same cluster ($a^i$).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the average distance from all data points in the closest cluster ($b^i$).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the coefficient:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[\frac{b^i - a^i}{max(a^i, b^i)}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coefficient can take values in the interval .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is 0 --&amp;gt; the sample is very close to the neighboring clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is 1 --&amp;gt; the sample is far away from the neighboring clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is -1 --&amp;gt; the sample is assigned to the wrong clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we want the coefficients to be as big as possible and close to 1 to have a good clusters. We&#39;ll use here geyser dataset again because its cheaper to run the silhouette analysis and it is actually obvious that there is most likely only two groups of data points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;for i, k in enumerate([2, 3, 4]):
    fig, (ax1, ax2) = plt.subplots(1, 2)
    fig.set_size_inches(18, 7)
    
    # Run the Kmeans algorithm
    km = KMeans(n_clusters=k)
    labels = km.fit_predict(X_std)
    centroids = km.cluster_centers_

    # Get silhouette samples
    silhouette_vals = silhouette_samples(X_std, labels)

    # Silhouette plot
    y_ticks = []
    y_lower, y_upper = 0, 0
    for i, cluster in enumerate(np.unique(labels)):
        cluster_silhouette_vals = silhouette_vals[labels == cluster]
        cluster_silhouette_vals.sort()
        y_upper += len(cluster_silhouette_vals)
        ax1.barh(range(y_lower, y_upper), cluster_silhouette_vals, edgecolor=&#39;none&#39;, height=1)
        ax1.text(-0.03, (y_lower + y_upper) / 2, str(i + 1))
        y_lower += len(cluster_silhouette_vals)

    # Get the average silhouette score and plot it
    avg_score = np.mean(silhouette_vals)
    ax1.axvline(avg_score, linestyle=&#39;--&#39;, linewidth=2, color=&#39;green&#39;)
    ax1.set_yticks([])
    ax1.set_xlim([-0.1, 1])
    ax1.set_xlabel(&#39;Silhouette coefficient values&#39;)
    ax1.set_ylabel(&#39;Cluster labels&#39;)
    ax1.set_title(&#39;Silhouette plot for the various clusters&#39;, y=1.02);
    
    # Scatter plot of data colored with labels
    ax2.scatter(X_std[:, 0], X_std[:, 1], c=labels)
    ax2.scatter(centroids[:, 0], centroids[:, 1], marker=&#39;*&#39;, c=&#39;r&#39;, s=250)
    ax2.set_xlim([-2, 2])
    ax2.set_xlim([-2, 2])
    ax2.set_xlabel(&#39;Eruption time in mins&#39;)
    ax2.set_ylabel(&#39;Waiting time to next eruption&#39;)
    ax2.set_title(&#39;Visualization of clustered data&#39;, y=1.02)
    ax2.set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;)
    plt.tight_layout()
    plt.suptitle(f&#39;Silhouette analysis using k = {k}&#39;,
                 fontsize=16, fontweight=&#39;semibold&#39;, y=1.05);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_2.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_2.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;





  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_3.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_3.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;





  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_4.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/silhouette_4.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the above plots show, &lt;code&gt;n_clusters=2&lt;/code&gt; has the best average silhouette score of around 0.75 and all clusters being above the average shows that it is actually a good choice. Also, the thickness of the silhouette plot gives an indication of how big each cluster is. The plot shows that cluster 1 has almost double the samples than cluster 2. However, as we increased &lt;code&gt;n_clusters&lt;/code&gt; to 3 and 4, the average silhouette score decreased dramatically to around 0.48 and 0.39 respectively. Moreover, the thickness of silhouette plot started showing wide fluctuations. The bottom line is: Good &lt;code&gt;n_clusters&lt;/code&gt; will have a well above 0.5 silhouette average score as well as all of the clusters have higher than the average score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;drawbacks&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Drawbacks
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kmeans algorithm is good in capturing structure of the data if clusters have a spherical-like shape. It always try to construct a nice spherical shape around the centroid. That means, the minute the clusters have a complicated geometric shapes, kmeans does a poor job in clustering the data. We&#39;ll illustrate three cases where kmeans will not perform well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, kmeans algorithm doesn&#39;t let data points that are far-away from each other share the same cluster even though they obviously belong to the same cluster. Below is an example of data points on two different horizontal lines that illustrates how kmeans tries to group half of the data points of each horizontal lines together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Create horizantal data
X = np.tile(np.linspace(1, 5, 20), 2)
y = np.repeat(np.array([2, 4]), 20)
df = np.c_[X, y]

km = KMeans(n_clusters=2)
km.fit(df)
labels = km.predict(df)
centroids = km.cluster_centers_

fig, ax = plt.subplots(figsize=(6, 6))
plt.scatter(X, y, c=labels)
plt.xlim([0, 6])
plt.ylim([0, 6])
plt.text(5.1, 4, &#39;A&#39;, color=&#39;red&#39;)
plt.text(5.1, 2, &#39;B&#39;, color=&#39;red&#39;)
plt.text(2.8, 4.1, &#39;C&#39;, color=&#39;red&#39;)
ax.set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/horizontal_cluster.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/horizontal_cluster.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kmeans considers the point &#39;B&#39; closer to point &#39;A&#39; than point &#39;C&#39; since they have non-spherical shape. Therefore, points &#39;A&#39; and &#39;B&#39; will be in the same cluster but point &#39;C&#39; will be in a different cluster. Note the &lt;strong&gt;Single Linkage&lt;/strong&gt; hierarchical clustering method gets this right because it doesn&#39;t separate similar points).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we&#39;ll generate data from multivariate normal distributions with different means and standard deviations. So we would have 3 groups of data where each group was generated from different multivariate normal distribution (different mean/standard deviation). One group will have a lot more data points than the other two combined. Next, we&#39;ll run kmeans on the data with $K = 3$ and see if it will be able to cluster the data correctly. To make the comparison easier, I am going to plot first the data colored based on the distribution it came from. Then I will plot the same data but now colored based on the clusters they have been assigned to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Create data from three different multivariate distributions
X_1 = np.random.multivariate_normal(mean=[4, 0], cov=[[1, 0], [0, 1]], size=75)
X_2 = np.random.multivariate_normal(mean=[6, 6], cov=[[2, 0], [0, 2]], size=250)
X_3 = np.random.multivariate_normal(mean=[1, 5], cov=[[1, 0], [0, 2]], size=20)
df = np.concatenate([X_1, X_2, X_3])

# Run kmeans
km = KMeans(n_clusters=3)
km.fit(df)
labels = km.predict(df)
centroids = km.cluster_centers_

# Plot the data
fig, ax = plt.subplots(1, 2, figsize=(10, 10))
ax[0].scatter(X_1[:, 0], X_1[:, 1])
ax[0].scatter(X_2[:, 0], X_2[:, 1])
ax[0].scatter(X_3[:, 0], X_3[:, 1])
ax[0].set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;)
ax[1].scatter(df[:, 0], df[:, 1], c=labels)
ax[1].scatter(centroids[:, 0], centroids[:, 1], marker=&#39;o&#39;,
                c=&amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, alpha=1, s=200, edgecolor=&#39;k&#39;)
for i, c in enumerate(centroids):
    ax[1].scatter(c[0], c[1], marker=&#39;$%d$&#39; % i, s=50, alpha=1, edgecolor=&#39;r&#39;)
ax[1].set_aspect(&#39;equal&#39;)
plt.tight_layout()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/random_data.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/random_data.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looks like kmeans couldn&#39;t figure out the clusters correctly. Since it tries to minimize the within-cluster variation, it gives more weight to bigger clusters than smaller ones. In other words, data points in smaller clusters may be left away from the centroid in order to focus more on the larger cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, we&#39;ll generate data that have complicated geometric shapes such as moons and circles within each other and test kmeans on both of the datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Cricles
X1 = make_circles(factor=0.5, noise=0.05, n_samples=1500)

# Moons
X2 = make_moons(n_samples=1500, noise=0.05)

fig, ax = plt.subplots(1, 2)
for i, X in enumerate([X1, X2]):
    fig.set_size_inches(18, 7)
    km = KMeans(n_clusters=2)
    km.fit(X[0])
    labels = km.predict(X[0])
    centroids = km.cluster_centers_

    ax[i].scatter(X[0][:, 0], X[0][:, 1], c=labels)
    ax[i].scatter(centroids[0, 0], centroids[0, 1], marker=&#39;*&#39;, s=400, c=&#39;r&#39;)
    ax[i].scatter(centroids[1, 0], centroids[1, 1], marker=&#39;+&#39;, s=300, c=&#39;green&#39;)
plt.suptitle(&#39;Simulated data&#39;, y=1.05, fontsize=22, fontweight=&#39;semibold&#39;)
plt.tight_layout()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/circles_wrong.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/circles_wrong.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As expected, kmeans couldn&#39;t figure out the correct clusters for both datasets. However, we can help kmeans perfectly cluster these kind of datasets if we use kernel methods. The idea is we transform to higher dimensional representation that make the data linearly separable (the same idea that we use in SVMs). Different kinds of algorithms work very well in such scenarios such as &lt;code&gt;SpectralClustering&lt;/code&gt;, see below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Cricles
X1 = make_circles(factor=0.5, noise=0.05, n_samples=1500)

# Moons
X2 = make_moons(n_samples=1500, noise=0.05)

fig, ax = plt.subplots(1, 2)
for i, X in enumerate([X1, X2]):
    fig.set_size_inches(18, 7)
    sp = SpectralClustering(n_clusters=2, affinity=&#39;nearest_neighbors&#39;)
    sp.fit(X[0])
    labels = sp.labels_
    ax[i].scatter(X[0][:, 0], X[0][:, 1], c=labels)
plt.suptitle(&#39;Simulated data&#39;, y=1.05, fontsize=22, fontweight=&#39;semibold&#39;)
plt.tight_layout()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/circles_right.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/kmeans/circles_right.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;conclusion&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Conclusion
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kmeans clustering is one of the most popular clustering algorithms and usually the first thing practitioners apply when solving clustering tasks to get an idea of the structure of the dataset. The goal of kmeans is to group data points into distinct non-overlapping subgroups. It does a very good job when the clusters have a kind of spherical shapes. However, it suffers as the geometric shapes of clusters deviates from spherical shapes. Moreover, it also doesn&#39;t learn the number of clusters from the data and requires it to be pre-defined. To be a good practitioner, it&#39;s good to know the assumptions behind algorithms/methods so that you would have a pretty good idea about the strength and weakness of each method. This will help you decide when to use each method and under what circumstances. In this post, we covered both strength, weaknesses, and some evaluation methods related to kmeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the main takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale/standardize the data when applying kmeans algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elbow method in selecting number of clusters doesn&#39;t usually work because the error function is monotonically decreasing for all $k$s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kmeans gives more weight to the bigger clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kmeans assumes spherical shapes of clusters (with radius equal to the distance between the centroid and the furthest data point) and doesn&#39;t work well when clusters are in different shapes such as elliptical clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is overlapping between clusters, kmeans doesn&#39;t have an intrinsic measure for uncertainty for the examples belong to the overlapping region in order to determine for which cluster to assign each data point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kmeans may still cluster the data even if it can&#39;t be clustered such as data that comes from &lt;em&gt;uniform distributions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notebook that created this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ImadDabbura/blog-posts/blob/master/notebooks/Kmeans-Clustering.ipynb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>epsilon-Greedy Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/epsilon-greedy-algorithm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/epsilon-greedy-algorithm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A/B testing can be defined as a randomized controlled experiment that allows us to test if there is a causal relationship between a change to a website/app and the user behavior. The change can be visible such as location of a button on the homepage or invisible such as the ranking/recommendation algorithms and backend infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web/Mobile developers and business stakeholders always face the following dilemma: Should we try out all ideas and explore all options continuously? Or should we exploit the best available option and stick to it?
The answer is, as in most cases, will be a trade-off between the two extremes. If we explore all the time, we&#39;ll collect a lot of data and waste resources in testing inferior ideas and missing sales (e-commerce case). However, if we only exploit the available option and never try new ideas, we would be left behind and loose in the long-term with ever-changing markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series, we&#39;ll explore solutions offered by &lt;strong&gt;Multi-armed Bandit Algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; that have two main advantages over traditional A/B testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smoothly decrease exploration over time instead of sudden jumps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus resources on better options and not keep evaluating inferior options during the life of the experiment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;strong&gt;Bandit Algorithms&lt;/strong&gt;? Bandit Algorithms are algorithms that try to learn a rule of selecting a sequence of options that balance exploring available options and getting enough knowledge about each option and maximize profits by selecting the best option. Note that during the experiment, we only have knowledge about the options we tried. Therefore, every time we select an option that&#39;s not the best one, we incur an opportunity cost of not selecting the best option; however, we also gain a new knowledge (feedback) about the selected option. In other words, we need to have enough feedback about each option to learn the best option. As a result, the best strategy would be to explore more at the beginning of the experiment until we know the best option and then start exploiting that option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
epsilon-Greedy Algorithm&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In this notebook, we&#39;ll cover &lt;strong&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;. Greedy Algorithm can be defined as the algorithm that picks the best currently available option without taking into consideration the long-term effect of that decision, which may happen to be a suboptimal decision. Given that, we can define epsilon-Greedy Algorithm as a Greedy Algorithm that adds some randomness when deciding between options: Instead of picking always the best available option, randomly explore other options with a probability = 𝜖 or pick the best option with a probability = 1 - 𝜖. Therefore, we can add randomness to the algorithm by increasing 𝜖, which will make the algorithm explores other options more frequently. Additionally, 𝜖 is a hyper-parameter that needs to be tuned based on the experiment, i.e. there is no value that works best on all experiments.
Let&#39;s explore how the algorithm works assuming we have two options: A and B (we can think of them as Control and Treatment groups). For each new user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume we have a coin that has a probability of coming heads = 𝜖 and a probability of coming tails = 1 - 𝜖. Therefore,

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it comes heads, explore randomly the available options (exploration).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The probability of selecting any option is 1/2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it comes tails, select the best option (exploitation).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the probability of selecting any option randomly if we have N options is 𝜖 1/N; however, the probability of selecting the best option is 1 - 𝜖 (see figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s import the needed packages and implement the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Import packages
import os
import sys

import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
import numpy as np
import seaborn as sns

# Add module path to system path
sys.path.append(os.path.abspath(&amp;quot;../&amp;quot;))
from utils import plot_algorithm, compare_algorithms

%matplotlib inline
plt.style.use(&amp;quot;fivethirtyeight&amp;quot;)
sns.set_context(&amp;quot;notebook&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class EpsilonGreedy:
    def __init__(self, epsilon, counts=None, values=None):
        self.epsilon = epsilon
        self.counts = counts
        self.values = values

    def initialize(self, n_arms):
        self.counts = np.zeros(n_arms, dtype=int)
        self.values = np.zeros(n_arms, dtype=float)

    def select_arm(self):
        z = np.random.random()
        if z &amp;gt; self.epsilon:
            # Pick the best arm
            return np.argmax(self.values)
        # Randomly pick any arm with prob 1 / len(self.counts)
        return np.random.randint(0, len(self.values))

    def update(self, chosen_arm, reward):
        # Increment chosen arm&#39;s count by one
        self.counts[chosen_arm] += 1
        n = self.counts[chosen_arm]

        # Recompute the estimated value of chosen arm using new reward
        value = self.values[chosen_arm]
        new_value = value * ((n - 1) / n) + reward / n
        self.values[chosen_arm] = new_value
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few things to note from the above implementation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialization of values (rewards) affect the long term performance of the algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The larger the sample size (N), the less influential the rewards from the recent options since we are using the average of each option in the values array.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Values array will store the estimated values (average) of each option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Counts is just an internal counter that keeps track of the number of times we selected each option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Monte Carlo Simulations&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In order to evaluate the algorithm, we will use Monte Carlo simulations. We&#39;ll use 5000 simulations to overcome the randomness generated from the random number generator. Also, we&#39;ll use Bernoulli distribution to get the reward from each option on each run. For each simulation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize the algorithm with no prior knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loop over the time horizon:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the reward for the selected option using Bernoulli distribution and the probability defined.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update the counts and estimated values of selected arm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll define the % of reward (probability) of each option and test the performance of the algorithm using three different metrics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability of selecting the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average rewards. This metric is a better approximation if the options are similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cumulative rewards. The previous two metrics are not fair metrics for algorithms with large epsilon where they sacrifice by exploring more options; however, cumulative rewards is what we should care about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we&#39;ll evaluate the algorithm using 5 different values of 𝜖: 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5. Since in the literature they use &lt;em&gt;arm&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;option&lt;/em&gt; for historical reasons, we&#39;ll be using &lt;em&gt;arm&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;option&lt;/em&gt; interchangeably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class BernoulliArm:
    def __init__(self, p):
        self.p = p

    def draw(self):
        z = np.random.random()
        if z &amp;gt; self.p:
            return 0.0
        return 1.0


def test_algorithm(algo, arms, num_simulations, horizon):
    # Initialize rewards and chosen_arms with zero 2d arrays
    chosen_arms = np.zeros((num_simulations, horizon))
    rewards = np.zeros((num_simulations, horizon))

    # Loop over all simulations
    for sim in range(num_simulations):
        # Re-initialize algorithm&#39;s counts and values arrays
        algo.initialize(len(arms))

        # Loop over all time horizon
        for t in range(horizon):
            # Select arm
            chosen_arm = algo.select_arm()
            chosen_arms[sim, t] = chosen_arm

            # Draw from Bernoulli distribution to get rewards
            reward = arms[chosen_arm].draw()
            rewards[sim, t] = reward

            # Update the algorithms&#39; count and estimated values
            algo.update(chosen_arm, reward)

    # Average rewards across all sims and compute cumulative rewards
    average_rewards = np.mean(rewards, axis=0)
    cumulative_rewards = np.cumsum(average_rewards)

    return chosen_arms, average_rewards, cumulative_rewards
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.random.seed(1)
# Average reward by arm
means = [0.1, 0.1, 0.1, 0.1, 0.9]
n_arms = len(means)
# Shuffle the arms
np.random.shuffle(means)
# Each arm will follow and Bernoulli distribution
arms = list(map(lambda mu: BernoulliArm(mu), means))
# Get the index of the best arm to test if algorithm will be able to learn that
best_arm_index = np.argmax(means)
# Define epsilon value to check the performance of the algorithm using each one
epsilon = [0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5]

# Plot the epsilon-Greedy algorithm
plot_algorithm(alg_name=&amp;quot;epsilon-Greedy&amp;quot;, arms=arms, best_arm_index=best_arm_index,
               hyper_params=epsilon, num_simulations=5000, horizon=500, label=&amp;quot;eps&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v1.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v1.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm: Vey Different Options.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Few thing to note from the above graphs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regardless of the epsilon values, all algorithms learned the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The algorithm picks options randomly; therefore, it&#39;s not guaranteed to always pick the best option even if it found that option. That&#39;s the main reason why none of the algorithms achieved a probability = 1 of selecting the best option or average rewards = % rewards of the best option even after they learned the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As 𝜖 increases --&amp;gt; increase the exploration --&amp;gt; increases the chance of picking options randomly instead of the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms with higher epsilon learn quicker but don&#39;t use that knowledge in exploiting the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using accuracy in picking the best option and average rewards metrics, the algorithm 𝜖 = 0.1 outperforms the rest; however, cumulative rewards metric shows that it takes that algorithm long time to outperform the algorithm with 𝜖 = 0.2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depends on time planned to run the experiment, different values of epsilons may be more optimal. For example, 𝜖 = 0.2 is the best value for almost anything at or below 400.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s run the experiment again to see how would the algorithm behave under the following settings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only two options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 option that are very similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.random.seed(1)
# Average reward by arm
means = [0.1, 0.9]
n_arms = len(means)
# Shuffle the arms
np.random.shuffle(means)
# Each arm will follow and Bernoulli distribution
arms = list(map(lambda mu: BernoulliArm(mu), means))
# Get the index of the best arm to test if algorithm will be able to learn that
best_arm_index = np.argmax(means)
# Define epsilon value to check the performance of the algorithm using each one
epsilon = [0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5]

# Plot the epsilon-Greedy algorithm
plot_algorithm(alg_name=&amp;quot;epsilon-Greedy&amp;quot;, arms=arms, best_arm_index=best_arm_index,
               hyper_params=epsilon, num_simulations=5000, horizon=500, label=&amp;quot;eps&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v2.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v2.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm: Two Options.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.random.seed(1)
# Average reward by arm
means = [i for i in np.random.random(50)]
n_arms = len(means)
# Shuffle the arms
np.random.shuffle(means)
# Each arm will follow and Bernoulli distribution
arms = list(map(lambda mu: BernoulliArm(mu), means))
# Get the index of the best arm to test if algorithm will be able to learn that
best_arm_index = np.argmax(means)
# Define epsilon value to check the performance of the algorithm using each one
epsilon = [0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5]

# Plot the epsilon-Greedy algorithm
plot_algorithm(alg_name=&amp;quot;epsilon-Greedy&amp;quot;, arms=arms, best_arm_index=best_arm_index,
               hyper_params=epsilon, num_simulations=5000, horizon=250, label=&amp;quot;eps&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v3.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v3.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm: Large Number of Options.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.random.seed(1)
# Average reward by arm
means = [0.2, 0.18, 0.22, 0.19, 0.21]
n_arms = len(means)
# Shuffle the arms
np.random.shuffle(means)
# Each arm will follow and Bernoulli distribution
arms = list(map(lambda mu: BernoulliArm(mu), means))
# Get the index of the best arm to test if algorithm will be able to learn that
best_arm_index = np.argmax(means)
# Define epsilon value to check the performance of the algorithm using each one
epsilon = [0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5]

# Plot the epsilon-Greedy algorithm
plot_algorithm(alg_name=&amp;quot;epsilon-Greedy&amp;quot;, arms=arms, best_arm_index=best_arm_index,
               hyper_params=epsilon, num_simulations=5000, horizon=500, label=&amp;quot;eps&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v4.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/epsilon_greedy_v4.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;epsilon-Greedy Algorithm: Very Similar Options.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we had lower number of options, all algorithms were faster at learning the best option which can be seen by the steepness of all curves of the first two graphs when time &amp;lt; 100. As a result, all algorithms had higher cumulative rewards than when we had 5 options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having large number of options made it hard on all algorithms to learn the best option and may need a lot more time to figure it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lastly, when options are very similar (in terms of rewards), the probability of selecting the best option by all algorithms decreases over time. Let&#39;s take the algorithm with 𝜖 = 0.1 and see why is this the case. After some investigation, the algorithm was struggling in differentiating between the best option and the second best option since the difference between the % rewards is 1%. Therefore, the probability of selecting the best arm was around 50%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Annealing epsilon-Greedy Algorithm&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Epsilon value plays a major role in the performance of epsilon-Greedy algorithm and has to be tuned to the best of our knowledge in terms of the expectations of the estimated rewards of each option. Nonetheless, this estimation suffers from high uncertainty since most of the times either we have no clue what might work or the results would be against our intuition as user experience research has shown in multiple studies. Therefore, isn&#39;t it nice if we can avoid setting up the epsilon values and make the algorithm parameter-free? That&#39;s what &lt;strong&gt;Annealing epsilon-Greedy Algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; does. We specify the rule of decaying epsilon with time and let the algorithm runs with no hyper-parameter configurations. The rule of we will use here is: 𝜖 = 1/&lt;em&gt;log(time + 0.0000001)&lt;/em&gt;. As we can see, at the beginning of the experiment, 𝜖 would be close to Inf and that means a lot of exploration; however, as time goes, 𝜖 start approaching zero and the algorithm would exploit more and more by selecting the best option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will evaluate the Annealed version using the same settings as before and compare it to standard version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class AnnealingEpsilonGreedy(EpsilonGreedy):
    def __init__(self, counts=None, values=None):
        self.counts = counts
        self.values = values

    def select_arm(self):
        # Epsilon decay schedule
        t = np.sum(self.counts) + 1
        epsilon = 1 / np.log(t + 0.0000001)

        z = np.random.random()
        if z &amp;gt; epsilon:
            # Pick the best arm
            return np.argmax(self.values)
        # Randomly pick any arm with prob 1 / len(self.counts)
        return np.random.randint(0, len(self.values))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.random.seed(1)
# Average reward by arm
means = [0.1, 0.1, 0.1, 0.1, 0.9]
n_arms = len(means)
# Shuffle the arms
np.random.shuffle(means)
# Each arm will follow and Bernoulli distribution
arms = list(map(lambda mu: BernoulliArm(mu), means))
# Get the index of the best arm to test if algorithm will be able to learn that
best_arm_index = np.argmax(means)

# Plot the epsilon-Greedy algorithm
plot_algorithm(alg_name=&amp;quot;Annealing epsilon-Greedy&amp;quot;, arms=arms, best_arm_index=best_arm_index,
               num_simulations=5000, horizon=500)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/annealing_epsilon_greedy.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/bandit-algorithms/annealing_epsilon_greedy.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Annealing epsilon-Greedy Algorithm.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even though the accuracy of selecting the best option and the average rewards of the annealing epsilon-Greedy Algorithm is lower than the standard version, it has higher cumulative rewards. Also, since the real world is uncertain and we may not have any clue about the designed options, it may be preferred to use the annealing version under some scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold\&#34;&gt;
Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
epsilon-Greedy Algorithm works by going back and forth between exploration with probability = 𝜖 and exploitation with probability 1 - 𝜖. Below are some takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting the value of epsilon:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we set 𝜖 = 1, we would only explore the available options with a probability = 1/N of selecting any option. This will enable us to explore a lot of ideas at the expense of wasting resources by evaluating inferior options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we set 𝜖 = 0, we would exploit the best option and never explore any new idea. This strategy would leave up behind our competitors given that the markets are so volatile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploration should be high at the beginning of the experiment to gain the knowledge about all the available options. It should decrease as a function of time where at some point after having enough data about all options, the algorithm should focus on exploiting the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All algorithms with different epsilon values learned the best option; however, they differ by the level of randomness of each algorithm in keep randomly exploring available options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the best results of any Bandit algorithm, we should have a lot of data, which means to run the experiment longer in most cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For experiments that run for short period of time, traditional A/B testing may be better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialization of estimated rewards can affect the long-term performance of the algorithm. As a result, we may need to use previous experience and intuition to guide our initial values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Source code that created this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ImadDabbura/blog-posts/blob/master/notebooks/epsilon-Greedy-Algorithm.ipynb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
The repo that hosts all Bandit Algorithms&#39; implementations and testing frameworks can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ImadDabbura/bandit-algorithms&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
The post is inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920027393.do&#34;&gt;Bandit Algorithms for Website Optimization&lt;/a&gt; book.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Loan Repayment</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/pred-loan-repayment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/pred-loan-repayment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The two most critical questions in the lending industry are: 1) How risky is the borrower? 2) Given the borrower&#39;s risk, should we lend him/her? The answer to the first question determines the interest rate the borrower would have. Interest rate measures among other things (such as time value of money) the riskness of the borrower, i.e. the riskier the borrower, the higher the interest rate. With interest rate in mind, we can then determine if the borrower is eligible for the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors (lenders) provide loans to borrowers in exchange for the promise of repayment with interest. That means the lender only makes profit (interest) if the borrower pays off the loan. However, if he/she doesn&#39;t repay the loan, then the lender loses money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll be using publicly available data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lendingclub.com/info/download-data.action&#34;&gt;LendingClub.com&lt;/a&gt;. The data covers the 9,578 loans funded by the platform between May 2007 and February 2010. The interest rate is provided to us for each borrower. Therefore, so we&#39;ll address the second question indirectly by trying to predict if the borrower will repay the loan by its mature date or not. Through this excerise we&#39;ll illustrate three modeling concepts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What to do with missing values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Techniques used with imbalanced classification problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrate how to build an ensemble model using two methods: blending and stacking, which most likely gives us a boost in performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a short description of each feature in the data set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;credit_policy&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 if the customer meets the credit underwriting criteria of LendingClub.com, and 0 otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: The purpose of the loan such as: credit_card, debt_consolidation, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;int_rate&lt;/strong&gt;: The interest rate of the loan (proportion).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;installment&lt;/strong&gt;: The monthly installments (\$) owed by the borrower if the loan is funded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;log_annual_inc&lt;/strong&gt;: The natural log of the annual income of the borrower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dti&lt;/strong&gt;: The debt-to-income ratio of the borrower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fico&lt;/strong&gt;: The FICO credit score of the borrower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;days_with_cr_line&lt;/strong&gt;: The number of days the borrower has had a credit line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;revol_bal&lt;/strong&gt;: The borrower&#39;s revolving balance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;revol_util&lt;/strong&gt;: The borrower&#39;s revolving line utilization rate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;inq_last_6mths&lt;/strong&gt;: The borrower&#39;s number of inquiries by creditors in the last 6 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;delinq_2yrs&lt;/strong&gt;: The number of times the borrower had been 30+ days past due on a payment in the past 2 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pub_rec&lt;/strong&gt;: The borrower&#39;s number of derogatory public records.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;not_fully_paid&lt;/strong&gt;: indicates whether the loan was not paid back in full (the borrower either defaulted or the borrower was deemed unlikely to pay it back).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s load the data and check:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data types of each feature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we have missing values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we have imbalanced data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source code that created this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ImadDabbura/blog-posts/blob/master/notebooks/Predicting-Loan-Repayment.ipynb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import os

import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
import numpy as np
import pandas as pd
import seaborn as sns
import fancyimpute
from imblearn.pipeline import make_pipeline as imb_make_pipeline
from imblearn.over_sampling import RandomOverSampler, SMOTE
from imblearn.under_sampling import RandomUnderSampler
from imblearn.ensemble import BalancedBaggingClassifier, EasyEnsemble
from mlens.visualization import corrmat
from sklearn.model_selection import train_test_split, cross_val_score, cross_val_predict
from sklearn.preprocessing import Imputer, RobustScaler, FunctionTransformer
from sklearn.ensemble import RandomForestClassifier, VotingClassifier, GradientBoostingClassifier
from sklearn.ensemble.partial_dependence import plot_partial_dependence
from sklearn.linear_model import LogisticRegression
from sklearn.svm import SVC, LinearSVC
from sklearn.neighbors import KNeighborsClassifier
from sklearn.metrics import (roc_auc_score, confusion_matrix,
                             accuracy_score, roc_curve,
                             precision_recall_curve, f1_score)
from sklearn.pipeline import make_pipeline
import xgboost as xgb
from keras import models, layers, optimizers

os.chdir(&amp;quot;../&amp;quot;)
from scripts.plot_roc import plot_roc_and_pr_curves
os.chdir(&amp;quot;notebooks/&amp;quot;)

%matplotlib inline
plt.style.use(&amp;quot;fivethirtyeight&amp;quot;)
sns.set_context(&amp;quot;notebook&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Load the data
df = pd.read_csv(&amp;quot;../data/loans.csv&amp;quot;)

# Check both the datatypes and if there is missing values
print(f&amp;quot;Data types:\n{11 * &#39;-&#39;}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;{df.dtypes}\n&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;Sum of null values in each feature:\n{35 * &#39;-&#39;}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;{df.isnull().sum()}&amp;quot;)
df.head()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Data types:
-----------
[30mcredit_policy          int64
purpose               object
int_rate             float64
installment          float64
log_annual_inc       float64
dti                  float64
fico                   int64
days_with_cr_line    float64
revol_bal              int64
revol_util           float64
inq_last_6mths       float64
delinq_2yrs          float64
pub_rec              float64
not_fully_paid         int64
dtype: object

Sum of null values in each feature:
-----------------------------------
[30mcredit_policy         0
purpose               0
int_rate              0
installment           0
log_annual_inc        4
dti                   0
fico                  0
days_with_cr_line    29
revol_bal             0
revol_util           62
inq_last_6mths       29
delinq_2yrs          29
pub_rec              29
not_fully_paid        0
dtype: int64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .dataframe thead tr:only-child th {
        text-align: right;
    }

    .dataframe thead th {
        text-align: left;
    }

    .dataframe tbody tr th {
        vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34; class=&#34;dataframe&#34;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;credit_policy&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;int_rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;installment&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;log_annual_inc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;dti&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;fico&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;days_with_cr_line&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_bal&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_util&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;inq_last_6mths&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;delinq_2yrs&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;pub_rec&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;not_fully_paid&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;debt_consolidation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1189&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;829.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19.48&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5639.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28854&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;52.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;credit_card&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1071&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.082143&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;707&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2760.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33623&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;debt_consolidation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1357&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;366.86&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.373491&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;682&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4710.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3511&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;debt_consolidation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;162.34&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;712&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2699.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;73.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;credit_card&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1426&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;102.92&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.299732&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.97&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4066.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4740&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Get number of positve and negative examples
pos = df[df[&amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;] == 1].shape[0]
neg = df[df[&amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;] == 0].shape[0]
print(f&amp;quot;Positive examples = {pos}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;Negative examples = {neg}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;Proportion of positive to negative examples = {(pos / neg) * 100:.2f}%&amp;quot;)
plt.figure(figsize=(8, 6))
sns.countplot(df[&amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;])
plt.xticks((0, 1), [&amp;quot;Paid fully&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Not paid fully&amp;quot;])
plt.xlabel(&amp;quot;&amp;quot;)
plt.ylabel(&amp;quot;Count&amp;quot;)
plt.title(&amp;quot;Class counts&amp;quot;, y=1, fontdict={&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 20});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Positive examples = 1533
Negative examples = 8045
Proportion of positive to negative examples = 19.06%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/class_counts.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/class_counts.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Class counts.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It looks like we have only one categorical feature (&amp;quot;purpose&amp;quot;). Also, six features have missing values (no missing values in labels). Moreover, the data set is pretty imbalanced as expected where positive examples (&amp;quot;not paid fully&amp;quot;) are only 19%. We&#39;ll explain in the next section how to handle all of them after giving an overview of ensemble methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Modeling&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ensemble methods&lt;/strong&gt; can be defined as combining several different models (base learners) into final model (meta learner) to reduce the generalization error. It relies on the assumption that each model would look at a different aspect of the data which yield to capturing part of the truth. Combining good performing models the were trained independently will capture more of the truth than a single model. Therefore, this would result in more accurate predictions and lower generalization errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost always ensemble model performance gets improved as we add more models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to combine models that are as much different as possible. This will reduce the correlation between the models that will improve the performance of the ensemble model that will lead to significantly outperform the best model. In the worst case where all models are perfectly correlated, the ensemble would have the same performance as the best model and sometimes even lower if some models are very bad. As a result, pick models that are as good as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diﬀerent ensemble methods construct the ensemble of models in diﬀerent ways. Below are the most common methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blending: Averaging the predictions of all models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bagging: Build different models on different datasets and then take the majority vote from all the models. Given the original dataset, we sample with replacement to get the same size of the original dataset. Therefore, each dataset will include, on average, 2/3 of the original data and the rest 1/3 will be duplicates. Since each model will be built on a different dataset, it can be seen as a different model. &lt;em&gt;Random Forest&lt;/em&gt; improves on default bagging trees by reducing the likelihood of strong features to picked on every split. In other words, it reduces the number of features available at each split from $n$ features to, for example, $n/2$ or $log(n)$ features. This will reduce correlation --&amp;gt; reduce variance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boosting: Build models sequentially. That means each model learns from the residuals of the previous model. The output will be all output of each single model weighted by the learning rate ($\lambda$). It reduces the bias resulted from bagging by learning sequentially from residuals of previous trees (models).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stacking: Build k models called base learners. Then fit a model to the output of the base learners to predict the final output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we&#39;ll be using Random Fores (bagging) and Gradient Boosting (boosting) classifiers as base learners in the ensemble model, we&#39;ll illustrate only averaging and stacking ensemble methods. Therefore, modeling parts would be consisted of three parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategies to deal with missing values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategies to deal with imbalanced datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build ensemble models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going further, the following data preprocessing steps will be applicable to all models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create dummy variables from the feature &amp;quot;purpose&amp;quot; since its nominal (not ordinal) categorical variable. It&#39;s also a good practice to drop the first one to avoid linear dependency between the resulted features since some algorithms may struggle with this issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split the data into training set (70%), and test set (30%). Training set will be used to fit the model, and test set will be to evaluate the best model to get an estimation of generalization error. Instead of having validation set to tune hyperparameters and evaluate different models, we&#39;ll use 10-folds cross validation because it&#39;s more reliable estimate of generalization error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standardize the data. We&#39;ll be using &lt;code&gt;RobustScaler&lt;/code&gt; so that the standarization will be less influenced by the outliers, i.e. more robust. It centers the data around the median and scale it using &lt;em&gt;interquartile range (IQR)&lt;/em&gt;. This step will be included in the pipelines for each model as a transformer so we will not do it separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Create dummy variables from the feature purpose
df = pd.get_dummies(df, columns=[&amp;quot;purpose&amp;quot;], drop_first=True)
df.head()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .dataframe thead tr:only-child th {
        text-align: right;
    }

    .dataframe thead th {
        text-align: left;
    }

    .dataframe tbody tr th {
        vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34; class=&#34;dataframe&#34;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;credit_policy&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;int_rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;installment&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;log_annual_inc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;dti&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;fico&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;days_with_cr_line&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_bal&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_util&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;inq_last_6mths&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;delinq_2yrs&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;pub_rec&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;not_fully_paid&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_credit_card&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_debt_consolidation&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_educational&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_home_improvement&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_major_purchase&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_small_business&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1189&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;829.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19.48&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5639.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28854&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;52.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1071&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.082143&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;707&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2760.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33623&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1357&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;366.86&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.373491&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;682&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4710.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3511&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;162.34&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;712&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2699.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;73.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1426&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;102.92&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.299732&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.97&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4066.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4740&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Strategies to deal with missing values&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Almost always real world data sets have missing values. This can be due, for example, users didn&#39;t fill some part of the forms or some transformations happened while collecting and cleaning the data before they send it to you. Sometimes missing values are informative and weren&#39;t generated randomly. Therefore, it&#39;s a good practice to add binary features to check if there is missing values in each row for each feature that has missing values. In our case, six features have missing values so we would add six binary features one for each feature. For example, &amp;quot;log_annual_inc&amp;quot; feature has missing values, so we would add a feature &amp;quot;is_log_annual_inc_missing&amp;quot; that takes the values $\in {0, 1}$. Good thing is that the missing values are in the predictors only and not the labels. Below are some of the most common strategies for dealing with missing values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simply delete all examples that have any missing values. This is usually done if the missing values are very small compared to the size of the data set and the missing values were random. In other words, the added binary features did not improve the model. One disadvantage for this strategy is that the model will throw an error when test data has missing values at prediction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impute the missing values using the mean of each feature separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impute the missing values using the median of each feature separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;em&gt;Multivariate Imputation by Chained Equations (MICE)&lt;/em&gt;. The main disadvantage of MICE is that we can&#39;t use it as a transformer in sklearn pipelines and it requires to use the full data set when imputing the missing values. This means that there will be a risk of data leakage since we&#39;re using both training and test sets to impute the missing values. The following steps explain how MICE works:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First step: Impute the missing values using the mean of each feature separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second step: For each feature that has missing values, we take all other features as predictors (including the ones that had missing values) and try to predict the values for this feature using linear regression for example. The predicted values will replace the old values for that feature. We do this for all features that have missing values, i.e. each feature will be used once as a target variable to predict its values and the rest of the time as a predictor to predict other features&#39; values. Therefore, one complete cycle (iteration) will be done once we run the model $k$ times to predict the $k$ features that have missing values. For our data set, each iteration will run the linear regression 6 times to predict the 6 features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third step: Repeat step 2 until there is not much of change between predictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impute the missing values using K-Nearest Neighbors. We compute distance between all examples (excluding missing values) in the data set and take the average of k-nearest neighbors of each missing value. There&#39;s no implementation for it yet in sklearn and it&#39;s pretty inefficient to compute it since we&#39;ll have to go through all examples to calculate distances. Therefore, we&#39;ll skip this strategy in this post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evaluate each strategy, we&#39;ll use &lt;em&gt;Random Forest&lt;/em&gt; classifier with hyperparameters&#39; values guided by &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1708.05070.pdf&#34;&gt;Data-driven Advice for Applying Machine Learning to Bioinformatics Problems&lt;/a&gt; as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s first create binary features for missing values and then prepare the data for each strategy discussed above. Next, we&#39;ll compute the 10-folds cross validation &lt;em&gt;AUC&lt;/em&gt; score for all the models using training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Create binary features to check if the example is has missing values for all features that have missing values
for feature in df.columns:
    if np.any(np.isnan(df[feature])):
        df[&amp;quot;is_&amp;quot; + feature + &amp;quot;_missing&amp;quot;] = np.isnan(df[feature]) * 1

df.head()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .dataframe thead tr:only-child th {
        text-align: right;
    }

    .dataframe thead th {
        text-align: left;
    }

    .dataframe tbody tr th {
        vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34; class=&#34;dataframe&#34;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;credit_policy&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;int_rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;installment&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;log_annual_inc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;dti&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;fico&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;days_with_cr_line&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_bal&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;revol_util&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;inq_last_6mths&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;...&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_educational&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_home_improvement&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_major_purchase&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;purpose_small_business&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_log_annual_inc_missing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_days_with_cr_line_missing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_revol_util_missing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_inq_last_6mths_missing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_delinq_2yrs_missing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;is_pub_rec_missing&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1189&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;829.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19.48&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5639.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28854&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;52.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1071&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.082143&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;707&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2760.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33623&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1357&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;366.86&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.373491&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;682&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4710.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3511&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;162.34&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.350407&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;712&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2699.958333&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;73.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1426&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;102.92&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.299732&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.97&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4066.000000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4740&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Original Data
X = df.loc[:, df.columns != &amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;].values
y = df.loc[:, df.columns == &amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;].values.flatten()
X_train, X_test, y_train, y_test = train_test_split(
    X, y, test_size=0.2, shuffle=True, random_state=123, stratify=y)
print(f&amp;quot;Original data shapes: {X_train.shape, X_test.shape}&amp;quot;)

# Drop NA and remove binary columns
train_indices_na = np.max(np.isnan(X_train), axis=1)
test_indices_na = np.max(np.isnan(X_test), axis=1)
X_train_dropna, y_train_dropna = X_train[~train_indices_na, :][:, :-6], y_train[~train_indices_na]
X_test_dropna, y_test_dropna = X_test[~test_indices_na, :][:, :-6], y_test[~test_indices_na]
print(f&amp;quot;After dropping NAs: {X_train_dropna.shape, X_test_dropna.shape}&amp;quot;)

# MICE data
mice = fancyimpute.MICE(verbose=0)
X_mice = mice.complete(X)
X_train_mice, X_test_mice, y_train_mice, y_test_mice = train_test_split(
    X_mice, y, test_size=0.2, shuffle=True, random_state=123, stratify=y)
print(f&amp;quot;MICE data shapes: {X_train_mice.shape, X_test_mice.shape}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Original data shapes: ((7662, 24), (1916, 24))
After dropping NAs: ((7611, 18), (1905, 18))
MICE data shapes: ((7662, 24), (1916, 24))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build random forest classifier
rf_clf = RandomForestClassifier(n_estimators=500,
                                max_features=0.25,
                                criterion=&amp;quot;entropy&amp;quot;,
                                class_weight=&amp;quot;balanced&amp;quot;)
# Build base line model -- Drop NA&#39;s
pip_baseline = make_pipeline(RobustScaler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_baseline,
                         X_train_dropna, y_train_dropna,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Baseline model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with mean imputation
pip_impute_mean = make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                                RobustScaler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_impute_mean,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Mean imputation model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with median imputation
pip_impute_median = make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;median&amp;quot;),
                                  RobustScaler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_impute_median,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Median imputation model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model using MICE imputation
pip_impute_mice = make_pipeline(RobustScaler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_impute_mice,
                         X_train_mice, y_train_mice,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;MICE imputation model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Baseline model&#39;s average AUC: 0.651
Mean imputation model&#39;s average AUC: 0.651
Median imputation model&#39;s average AUC: 0.651
MICE imputation model&#39;s average AUC: 0.656
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s plot the feature importances to check if the added binary features added anything to the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# fit RF to plot feature importances
rf_clf.fit(RobustScaler().fit_transform(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;median&amp;quot;).fit_transform(X_train)), y_train)

# Plot features importance
importances = rf_clf.feature_importances_
indices = np.argsort(rf_clf.feature_importances_)[::-1]
plt.figure(figsize=(12, 6))
plt.bar(range(1, 25), importances[indices], align=&amp;quot;center&amp;quot;)
plt.xticks(range(1, 25), df.columns[df.columns != &amp;quot;not_fully_paid&amp;quot;][indices], rotation=90)
plt.title(&amp;quot;Feature Importance&amp;quot;, {&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 16});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/feature_importance.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/feature_importance.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Random Forest feature importance.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Guided by the 10-fold cross validation &lt;em&gt;AUC&lt;/em&gt; scores, it looks like all strategies have comparable results and missing values were generated randomly. Also, the added six binary features showed no importance when plotting feature importances from &lt;em&gt;Random Forest&lt;/em&gt; classifier. Therefore, it&#39;s safe to drop those features and use &lt;em&gt;Median Imputation&lt;/em&gt; method as a transformer later on in the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Drop generated binary features
X_train = X_train[:, :-6]
X_test = X_test[:, :-6]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Strategies to deal with imbalanced datasets&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Classification problems in most real world applications have imbalanced data sets. In other words, the positive examples (minority class) are a lot less than negative examples (majority class). We can see that in spam detection, ads click, loan approvals, etc. In our example, the positive examples (people who haven&#39;t fully paid) were only 19% from the total examples. Therefore, accuracy is no longer a good measure of performance for different models because if we simply predict all examples to belong to the negative class, we achieve 81% accuracy. Better metrics for imbalanced data sets are &lt;em&gt;AUC&lt;/em&gt; (area under the ROC curve) and f1-score. However, that&#39;s not enough because class imbalance influences a learning algorithm during training by making the decision rule biased towards the majority class by implicitly learns a model that optimizes the predictions based on the majority class in the dataset. As a result, we&#39;ll explore different methods to overcome class imbalance problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under-Sample: Under-sample the majority class with or w/o replacement by making the number of positive and negative examples equal. One of the drawbacks of under-sampling is that it ignores a good portion of training data that has valuable information. In our example, it would loose around 6500 examples. However, it&#39;s very fast to train.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over-Sample: Over-sample the minority class with or w/o replacement by making the number of positive and negative examples equal. We&#39;ll add around 6500 samples from the training data set with this strategy. It&#39;s a lot more computationally expensive than under-sampling. Also, it&#39;s more prune to overfitting due to repeated examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EasyEnsemble: Sample several subsets from the majority class, build a classifier on top of each sampled data, and combine the output of all classifiers. More details can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.nju.edu.cn/zhouzh/zhouzh.files/publication/tsmcb09.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE): It over-samples the minority class but using synthesized examples. It operates on feature space not the data space. Here how it works:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the k-nearest neighbors for all minority samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Randomly choose number between 1-k.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each feature:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the difference between minority sample and its randomly chosen neighbor (from previous step).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiply the difference by random number between 0 and 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the obtained feature to the synthesized sample attributes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the above until we get the number of synthesized samples needed. More information can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jair.org/media/953/live-953-2037-jair.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other methods such as &lt;code&gt;EditedNearestNeighbors&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CondensedNearestNeighbors&lt;/code&gt; that we will not cover in this post and are rarely used in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most applications, misclassifying the minority class (false negative) is a lot more expensive than misclassifying the majority class (false positive). In the context of lending, loosing money by lending to a risky borrower who is more likely to not fully pay the loan back is a lot more costly than missing the opportunity of lending to trust-worthy borrower (less risky). As a result, we can use &lt;code&gt;class_weight&lt;/code&gt; that changes the weight of misclassifying positive example in the loss function. Also, we can use different cut-offs assign examples to classes. By default, 0.5 is the cut-off; however, we see more often in applications such as lending that the cut-off is less than 0.5. Note that changing the cut-off from the default 0.5 reduce the overall accuracy but may improve the accuracy of predicting positive/negative examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll evaluate all the above methods plus the original model without resampling as a baseline model using the same &lt;em&gt;Random Forest&lt;/em&gt; classifier we used in the missing values section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build random forest classifier (same config)
rf_clf = RandomForestClassifier(n_estimators=500,
                                max_features=0.25,
                                criterion=&amp;quot;entropy&amp;quot;,
                                class_weight=&amp;quot;balanced&amp;quot;)

# Build model with no sampling
pip_orig = make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                         RobustScaler(),
                         rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_orig,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Original model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with undersampling
pip_undersample = imb_make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                                    RobustScaler(),
                                    RandomUnderSampler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_undersample,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Under-sampled model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with oversampling
pip_oversample = imb_make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                                    RobustScaler(),
                                    RandomOverSampler(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_oversample,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;Over-sampled model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with EasyEnsemble
resampled_rf = BalancedBaggingClassifier(base_estimator=rf_clf,
                                         n_estimators=10, random_state=123)
pip_resampled = make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                              RobustScaler(), resampled_rf)
                             
scores = cross_val_score(pip_resampled,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;EasyEnsemble model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)

# Build model with SMOTE
pip_smote = imb_make_pipeline(Imputer(strategy=&amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;),
                              RobustScaler(),
                              SMOTE(), rf_clf)
scores = cross_val_score(pip_smote,
                         X_train, y_train,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;roc_auc&amp;quot;, cv=10)
print(f&amp;quot;SMOTE model&#39;s average AUC: {scores.mean():.3f}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Original model&#39;s average AUC: 0.652
Under-sampled model&#39;s average AUC: 0.656
Over-sampled model&#39;s average AUC: 0.651
EasyEnsemble model&#39;s average AUC: 0.665
SMOTE model&#39;s average AUC: 0.641
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EasyEnsemble method has the highest 10-folds CV with average AUC = 0.665.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:1.5em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Build Ensemble models&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br&gt;
We&#39;ll build ensemble models using three different models as base learners:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gradient Boosting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support Vector Classifier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random Forest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ensemble models will be built using two different methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blending (average) ensemble model. Fits the base learners to the training data and then, at test time, average the predictions generated by all the base learners.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use VotingClassifier from sklearn that:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fits all the base learners on the training data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At test time, use all base learners to predict test data and then take the average of all predictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stacked ensemble model: Fits the base learners to the training data. Next, use those trained base learners to generate predictions (meta-features) used by the meta-learner (assuming we have only one layer of base learners). There are few different ways of training stacked ensemble model:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fitting the base learners to all training data and then generate predictions using the same training data it was used to fit those learners. This method is more prune to overfitting because the meta learner will give more weights to the base learner who memorized the training data better, i.e. meta-learner won&#39;t generate well and would overfit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split the training data into 2 to 3 different parts that will be used for training, validation, and generate predictions. It&#39;s a suboptimal method because held out sets usually have higher variance and different splits give different results as well as learning algorithms would have fewer data to train.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use k-folds cross validation where we split the data into k-folds. We fit the base learners to the (k - 1) folds and use the fitted models to generate predictions of the held out fold. We repeat the process until we generate the predictions for all the k-folds. When done, refit the base learners to the full training data. This method is more reliable and will give models that memorize the data less weight. Therefore, it generalizes better on future data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll use logistic regression as the meta-learner for the stacked model. Note that we can use k-folds cross validation to validate and tune the hyperparameters of the meta learner. We will not tune the hyperparameters of any of the base learners or the meta-learner; however, we will use some of the values recommended by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1708.05070.pdf&#34;&gt;Pennsylvania Benchmarking Paper&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, we won&#39;t use EasyEnsemble in training because, after some experimentation, it didn&#39;t improve the AUC of the ensemble model more than 2% on average and it was computationally very expensive. In practice, we sometimes are willing to give up small improvements if the model would become a lot more complex computationally. Therefore, we will use &lt;code&gt;RandomUnderSampler&lt;/code&gt;. Also, we&#39;ll impute the missing values and standardize the data beforehand so that it would shorten the code of the ensemble models and allows use to avoid using &lt;code&gt;Pipeline&lt;/code&gt;. Additionally, we will plot ROC and PR curves using test data and evaluate the performance of all models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Impute the missing data using features means
imp = Imputer()
imp.fit(X_train)
X_train = imp.transform(X_train)
X_test = imp.transform(X_test)

# Standardize the data
std = RobustScaler()
std.fit(X_train)
X_train = std.transform(X_train)
X_test = std.transform(X_test)

# Implement RandomUnderSampler
random_undersampler = RandomUnderSampler()
X_res, y_res = random_undersampler.fit_sample(X_train, y_train)
# Shuffle the data
perms = np.random.permutation(X_res.shape[0])
X_res = X_res[perms]
y_res = y_res[perms]
X_res.shape, y_res.shape
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;((2452, 18), (2452,))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Define base learners
xgb_clf = xgb.XGBClassifier(objective=&amp;quot;binary:logistic&amp;quot;,
                            learning_rate=0.03,
                            n_estimators=500,
                            max_depth=1,
                            subsample=0.4,
                            random_state=123)

svm_clf = SVC(gamma=0.1,
                C=0.01,
                kernel=&amp;quot;poly&amp;quot;,
                degree=3,
                coef0=10.0,
                probability=True)

rf_clf = RandomForestClassifier(n_estimators=300,
                                max_features=&amp;quot;sqrt&amp;quot;,
                                criterion=&amp;quot;gini&amp;quot;,
                                min_samples_leaf=5,
                                class_weight=&amp;quot;balanced&amp;quot;)

# Define meta-learner
logreg_clf = LogisticRegression(penalty=&amp;quot;l2&amp;quot;,
                                C=100,
                                fit_intercept=True)

# Fitting voting clf --&amp;gt; average ensemble
voting_clf = VotingClassifier([(&amp;quot;xgb&amp;quot;, xgb_clf),
                               (&amp;quot;svm&amp;quot;, svm_clf),
                               (&amp;quot;rf&amp;quot;, rf_clf)],
                              voting=&amp;quot;soft&amp;quot;,
                              flatten_transform=True)
voting_clf.fit(X_res, y_res)
xgb_model, svm_model, rf_model = voting_clf.estimators_
models = {&amp;quot;xgb&amp;quot;: xgb_model, &amp;quot;svm&amp;quot;: svm_model,
          &amp;quot;rf&amp;quot;: rf_model, &amp;quot;avg_ensemble&amp;quot;: voting_clf}

# Build first stack of base learners
first_stack = make_pipeline(voting_clf,
                            FunctionTransformer(lambda X: X[:, 1::2]))
# Use CV to generate meta-features
meta_features = cross_val_predict(first_stack,
                                  X_res, y_res,
                                  cv=10,
                                  method=&amp;quot;transform&amp;quot;)
# Refit the first stack on the full training set
first_stack.fit(X_res, y_res)
# Fit the meta learner
second_stack = logreg_clf.fit(meta_features, y_res)

# Plot ROC and PR curves using all models and test data
fig, axes = plt.subplots(1, 2, figsize=(14, 6))
for name, model in models.items():
            model_probs = model.predict_proba(X_test)[:, 1:]
            model_auc_score = roc_auc_score(y_test, model_probs)
            fpr, tpr, _ = roc_curve(y_test, model_probs)
            precision, recall, _ = precision_recall_curve(y_test, model_probs)
            axes[0].plot(fpr, tpr, label=f&amp;quot;{name}, auc = {model_auc_score:.3f}&amp;quot;)
            axes[1].plot(recall, precision, label=f&amp;quot;{name}&amp;quot;)
stacked_probs = second_stack.predict_proba(first_stack.transform(X_test))[:, 1:]
stacked_auc_score = roc_auc_score(y_test, stacked_probs)
fpr, tpr, _ = roc_curve(y_test, stacked_probs)
precision, recall, _ = precision_recall_curve(y_test, stacked_probs)
axes[0].plot(fpr, tpr, label=f&amp;quot;stacked_ensemble, auc = {stacked_auc_score:.3f}&amp;quot;)
axes[1].plot(recall, precision, label=&amp;quot;stacked_ensembe&amp;quot;)
axes[0].legend(loc=&amp;quot;lower right&amp;quot;)
axes[0].set_xlabel(&amp;quot;FPR&amp;quot;)
axes[0].set_ylabel(&amp;quot;TPR&amp;quot;)
axes[0].set_title(&amp;quot;ROC curve&amp;quot;)
axes[1].legend()
axes[1].set_xlabel(&amp;quot;recall&amp;quot;)
axes[1].set_ylabel(&amp;quot;precision&amp;quot;)
axes[1].set_title(&amp;quot;PR curve&amp;quot;)
plt.tight_layout()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/roc_pr_curve.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/roc_pr_curve.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;ROC and PR curves.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we can see from the chart above, stacked ensemble model didn&#39;t improve the performance. One of the major reasons are that the base learners are considerably highly correlated especially &lt;em&gt;Random Forest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gradient Boosting&lt;/em&gt; (see the correlation matrix below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Plot the correlation between base learners
probs_df = pd.DataFrame(meta_features, columns=[&amp;quot;xgb&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;svm&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;rf&amp;quot;])
corrmat(probs_df.corr(), inflate=True);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/corr_matrix.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/corr_matrix.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Correlation matrix.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition, with classification problems where False Negatives are a lot more expensive than False Positives, we may want to have a model with a high precision rather than high recall, i.e. the probability of the model to identify positive examples from randomly selected examples. Below is the confusion matrix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;second_stack_probs = second_stack.predict_proba(first_stack.transform(X_test))
second_stack_preds = second_stack.predict(first_stack.transform(X_test))
conf_mat = confusion_matrix(y_test, second_stack_preds)
# Define figure size and figure ratios
plt.figure(figsize=(16, 8))
plt.matshow(conf_mat, cmap=plt.cm.Reds, alpha=0.2)
for i in range(2):
    for j in range(2):
        plt.text(x=j, y=i, s=conf_mat[i, j], ha=&amp;quot;center&amp;quot;, va=&amp;quot;center&amp;quot;)
plt.title(&amp;quot;Confusion matrix&amp;quot;, y=1.1, fontdict={&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 20})
plt.xlabel(&amp;quot;Predicted&amp;quot;, fontdict={&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 14})
plt.ylabel(&amp;quot;Actual&amp;quot;, fontdict={&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 14});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/confusion_matrix.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/confusion_matrix.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Confusion matrix.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s finally check the partial dependence plots to see what are the most important features and their relationships with whether the borrower will most likely pay the loan in full before mature data. we will plot only the top 8 features to make it easier to read. Note that the partial plots are based on Gradient Boosting model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Plot partial dependence plots
gbrt = GradientBoostingClassifier(loss=&amp;quot;deviance&amp;quot;,
                                  learning_rate=0.1,
                                  n_estimators=100,
                                  max_depth=3,
                                  random_state=123)
gbrt.fit(X_res, y_res)
fig, axes = plot_partial_dependence(gbrt, X_res,
                                    np.argsort(gbrt.feature_importances_)[::-1][:8],
                                    n_cols=4,
                                    feature_names=df.columns[:-6],
                                    figsize=(14, 8))
plt.subplots_adjust(top=0.9)
plt.suptitle(&amp;quot;Partial dependence plots of borrower not fully paid\n&amp;quot;
             &amp;quot;the loan based on top most influential features&amp;quot;)
for ax in axes: ax.set_xticks(())
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/partial_plots.png&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/loan-repayment/partial_plots.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Partial dependence plots.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we might expected, borrowers with lower annual income and less FICO scores are less likely to pay the loan fully; however, borrowers with lower interest rates (riskier) and smaller installments are more likely to pay the loan fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size:2em;color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Most classification problems in the real world are imbalanced. Also, almost always data sets have missing values. In this post, we covered strategies to deal with both missing values and imbalanced data sets. We also explored different ways of building ensembles in sklearn. Below are some takeaway points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no definitive guide of which algorithms to use given any situation. What may work on some data sets may not necessarily work on others. Therefore, always evaluate methods using cross validation to get a reliable estimates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes we may be willing to give up some improvement to the model if that would increase the complexity much more than the percentage change in the improvement to the evaluation metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In some classification problems, &lt;em&gt;False Negatives&lt;/em&gt; are a lot more expensive than &lt;em&gt;False Positives&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, we can reduce cut-off points to reduce the False Negatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When building ensemble models, try to use good models that are as different as possible to reduce correlation between the base learners. We could&#39;ve enhanced our stacked ensemble model by adding &lt;em&gt;Dense Neural Network&lt;/em&gt; and some other kind of base learners as well as adding more layers to the stacked model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EasyEnsemble usually performs better than any other resampling methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Missing values sometimes add more information to the model than we might expect. One way of capturing it is to add binary features for each feature that has missing values to check if each example is missing or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Employee Turnover</title>
      <link>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/pred-employee-turnover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://imaddabbura.github.io/post/pred-employee-turnover/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Employee turnover&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the percentage of workers who leave an organization and are replaced by new employees. It is very costly for organizations, where costs include but not limited to: separation, vacancy, recruitment, training and replacement. On average, organizations invest between four weeks and three months training new employees. This investment would be a loss for the company if the new employee decided to leave the first year. Furthermore, organizations such as consulting firms would suffer from deterioration in customer satisfaction due to regular changes in &lt;em&gt;Account Reps&lt;/em&gt; and/or &lt;em&gt;Consultants&lt;/em&gt; that would lead to loss of businesses with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll work on simulated HR data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/ludobenistant/hr-analytics-1&#34;&gt;kaggle&lt;/a&gt; to build a classifier that helps us predict what kind of employees will be more likely to leave given some attributes. Such classifier would help an organization predict employee turnover and be pro-active in helping to solve such costly matter. We’ll restrict ourselves to use the most common classifiers: Random Forest, Gradient Boosting Trees, K-Nearest Neighbors, Logistic Regression and Support Vector Machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data has 14,999 examples (samples). Below are the features and the definitions of each one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;satisfaction_level: Level of satisfaction {0–1}.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;last_evaluationTime: Time since last performance evaluation (in years).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number_project: Number of projects completed while at work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;average_montly_hours: Average monthly hours at workplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time_spend_company: Number of years spent in the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work_accident: Whether the employee had a workplace accident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left: Whether the employee left the workplace or not {0, 1}.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promotion_last_5years: Whether the employee was promoted in the last five years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sales: Department the employee works for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salary: Relative level of salary {low, medium, high}.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source code that created this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ImadDabbura/blog-posts/blob/master/notebooks/Employee-Turnover.ipynb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 2em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Data Preprocessing
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the data (check if there are missing values and the data type of each features):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Load the data
df = pd.read_csv(“data/HR_comma_sep.csv”)
# Check both the datatypes and if there is missing values
print(“\033[1m” + “\033[94m” + “Data types:\n” + 11 * “-”)
print(“\033[30m” + “{}\n”.format(df.dtypes))
print(“\033[1m” + “\033[94m” + “Sum of null values in each column:\n” + 35 * “-”)
print(“\033[30m” + “{}”.format(df.isnull().sum()))
df.head()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/data_types.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/data_types.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Data overview.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since there are no missing values, we do not have to do any imputation. However, there are some data preprocessing needed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change &lt;strong&gt;sales&lt;/strong&gt; feature name to &lt;strong&gt;department&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert &lt;strong&gt;salary&lt;/strong&gt; into ordinal categorical feature since there is intrinsic order between: low, medium and high.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create dummy features from &lt;strong&gt;department&lt;/strong&gt; feature and drop the first one to avoid linear dependency where some learning algorithms may struggle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Rename sales feature into department
df = df.rename(columns={&amp;quot;sales&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;department&amp;quot;})
# Map salary into integers
salary_map = {&amp;quot;low&amp;quot;: 0, &amp;quot;medium&amp;quot;: 1, &amp;quot;high&amp;quot;: 2}
df[&amp;quot;salary&amp;quot;] = df[&amp;quot;salary&amp;quot;].map(salary_map)
# Create dummy variables for department feature
df = pd.get_dummies(df, columns=[&amp;quot;department&amp;quot;], drop_first=True)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is now ready to be used for modeling. The final number of features are now 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 2em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Modeling
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first take a look at the proportion of each class to see if we’re dealing with balanced or imbalanced data, since each one has its own set of tools to be used when fitting classifiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Get number of positve and negative examples
pos = df[df[&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;] == 1].shape[0]
neg = df[df[&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;] == 0].shape[0]
print(&amp;quot;Positive examples = {}&amp;quot;.format(pos))
print(&amp;quot;Negative examples = {}&amp;quot;.format(neg))
print(&amp;quot;Proportion of positive to negative examples = {:.2f}%&amp;quot;.format((pos / neg) * 100))
sns.countplot(df[&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;])
plt.xticks((0, 1), [&amp;quot;Didn&#39;t leave&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Left&amp;quot;])
plt.xlabel(&amp;quot;Left&amp;quot;)
plt.ylabel(&amp;quot;Count&amp;quot;)
plt.title(&amp;quot;Class counts&amp;quot;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/class_counts.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/class_counts.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Class counts.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the graph shows, we have an imbalanced dataset. As a result, when we fit classifiers on such datasets, we should use metrics other than accuracy when comparing models such as &lt;em&gt;f1-score&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;AUC&lt;/em&gt; (area under ROC curve). Moreover, class imbalance influences a learning algorithm during training by making the decision rule biased towards the majority class by implicitly learns a model that optimizes the predictions based on the majority class in the dataset. There are three ways to deal with this issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign a larger penalty to wrong predictions from the minority class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upsampling the minority class or downsampling the majority class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate synthetic training examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there is no definitive guide or best practices to deal with such situations. Therefore, we have to try them all and see which one works best for the problem on hand. We’ll restrict ourselves to use the first two, i.e, assign larger penalty to wrong predictions from the minority class using &lt;code&gt;class_weight&lt;/code&gt; in classifiers that allows us do that and evaluate upsampling/downsampling on the training data to see which gives higher performance.
First, split the data into training and test sets using 80/20 split; 80% of the data will be used to train the models and 20% to test the performance of the models. Second, Upsample the minority class and downsample the majority class. For this data set, positive class is the minority class and negative class is the majority class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Convert dataframe into numpy objects and split them into
# train and test sets: 80/20
X = df.loc[:, df.columns != &amp;quot;left&amp;quot;].values
y = df.loc[:, df.columns == &amp;quot;left&amp;quot;].values.flatten()
X_train, X_test, y_train, y_test = train_test_split(
    X, y, test_size=0.2, stratify=y, random_state=1)
# Upsample minority class
X_train_u, y_train_u = resample(X_train[y_train == 1],
                                y_train[y_train == 1],
                                replace=True,
                                n_samples=X_train[y_train == 0].shape[0],
                                random_state=1)
X_train_u = np.concatenate((X_train[y_train == 0], X_train_u))
y_train_u = np.concatenate((y_train[y_train == 0], y_train_u))
# Downsample majority class
X_train_d, y_train_d = resample(X_train[y_train == 0],
                                y_train[y_train == 0],
                                replace=True,
                                n_samples=X_train[y_train == 1].shape[0],
                                random_state=1)
X_train_d = np.concatenate((X_train[y_train == 1], X_train_d))
y_train_d = np.concatenate((y_train[y_train == 1], y_train_d))
print(&amp;quot;Original shape:&amp;quot;, X_train.shape, y_train.shape)
print(&amp;quot;Upsampled shape:&amp;quot;, X_train_u.shape, y_train_u.shape)
print(&amp;quot;Downsampled shape:&amp;quot;, X_train_d.shape, y_train_d.shape)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Original shape: (11999, 17) (11999,)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upsampled shape: (18284, 17) (18284,)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downsampled shape: (5714, 17) (5714,)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we need to apply dimensionality reduction such as PCA because: 1) We want to know the importance of each feature in determining who will leave versus who will not (inference). 2) Dimension of the data set is decent (17 features). However, it’s good to see how many principal components needed to explain 90%, 95% and 99% of the variation in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build PCA using standarized trained data
pca = PCA(n_components=None, svd_solver=&amp;quot;full&amp;quot;)
pca.fit(StandardScaler().fit_transform(X_train))
cum_var_exp = np.cumsum(pca.explained_variance_ratio_)
plt.figure(figsize=(12, 6))
plt.bar(range(1, 18), pca.explained_variance_ratio_, align=&amp;quot;center&amp;quot;,
        color=&#39;red&#39;, label=&amp;quot;Individual explained variance&amp;quot;)
plt.step(range(1, 18), cum_var_exp, where=&amp;quot;mid&amp;quot;, label=&amp;quot;Cumulative explained variance&amp;quot;)
plt.xticks(range(1, 18))
plt.legend(loc=&amp;quot;best&amp;quot;)
plt.xlabel(&amp;quot;Principal component index&amp;quot;, {&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 14})
plt.ylabel(&amp;quot;Explained variance ratio&amp;quot;, {&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 14})
plt.title(&amp;quot;PCA on training data&amp;quot;, {&amp;quot;fontsize&amp;quot;: 16});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/PCA.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/PCA.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;PCA.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looks like it needs 14, 15 and 16 principal components to capture 90%, 95% and 99% of the variation in the data respectively. In other words, this means that the data is already in a good space since eigenvalues are very close to each other and gives further evidence that we don’t need to compress the data.
The methodology that we’ll follow when building the classifiers goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a pipeline that handles all the steps when fitting the classifier using scikit-learn’s &lt;code&gt;make_pipeline&lt;/code&gt; which will have two steps:
I. Standardizing the data to speed up convergence and make all features on the same scale.
II. The classifier (&lt;code&gt;estimator&lt;/code&gt;) we want to use to fit the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;GridSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; to tune hyperparameters using 10-folds cross validation. We can use &lt;code&gt;RandomizedSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; which is faster and may outperform &lt;code&gt;GridSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; especially if we have more than two hyperparameters and the range for each one is very big; however, &lt;code&gt;GridSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; will work just fine since we have only two hyperparameters and descent range.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fit the model using training data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plot both confusion matrix and ROC curve for the best estimator using test data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeat the above steps for &lt;em&gt;Random Forest, Gradient Boosting Trees, K-Nearest Neighbors, Logistic Regression and Support Vector Machine&lt;/em&gt;. Next, pick the classifier that has the highest cross validation f1 score. Note: some of the hyperparameter ranges will be guided by the paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1708.05070.pdf&#34;&gt;Data-driven Advice for Applying Machine Learning to Bioinformatics Problems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 1.5em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Random Forest
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we will start by fitting a Random Forest classifier using &lt;em&gt;unsampled, upsampled and downsampled&lt;/em&gt; data. Second, we will evaluate each method using cross validation (CV) f1-score and pick the one with the highest CV f1-score. Finally, we will use that method to fit the rest of the classifiers.
The only hyperparameters we’ll tune are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;max_feature&lt;/code&gt;: how many features to consider randomly on each split. This will help avoid having few strong features to be picked on each split and let other features have the chance to contribute. Therefore, predictions will be less correlated and the variance of each tree will decrease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;min_samples_leaf&lt;/code&gt;: how many examples to have for each split to be a final leaf node.
Random Forest is an ensemble model that has multiple trees (&lt;code&gt;n_estimators&lt;/code&gt;). The final prediction would be a weighting average (regression) or mode (classification) of the predictions from all estimators. Note: a high number of trees doesn&#39;t cause overfitting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build random forest classifier
methods_data = {&amp;quot;Original&amp;quot;: (X_train, y_train),
                &amp;quot;Upsampled&amp;quot;: (X_train_u, y_train_u),
                &amp;quot;Downsampled&amp;quot;: (X_train_d, y_train_d)}
for method in methods_data.keys():
    pip_rf = make_pipeline(StandardScaler(),
                           RandomForestClassifier(n_estimators=500,
                                                  class_weight=&amp;quot;balanced&amp;quot;,
                                                  random_state=123))
    
    hyperparam_grid = {
        &amp;quot;randomforestclassifier__n_estimators&amp;quot;: [10, 50, 100, 500],
        &amp;quot;randomforestclassifier__max_features&amp;quot;: [&amp;quot;sqrt&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;log2&amp;quot;, 0.4, 0.5],
        &amp;quot;randomforestclassifier__min_samples_leaf&amp;quot;: [1, 3, 5],
        &amp;quot;randomforestclassifier__criterion&amp;quot;: [&amp;quot;gini&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;entropy&amp;quot;]}
    
    gs_rf = GridSearchCV(pip_rf,
                         hyperparam_grid,
                         scoring=&amp;quot;f1&amp;quot;,
                         cv=10,
                         n_jobs=-1)
    
    gs_rf.fit(methods_data[method][0], methods_data[method][1])
    
    print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[0m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;The best hyperparameters for {} data:&amp;quot;.format(method))
    for hyperparam in gs_rf.best_params_.keys():
        print(hyperparam[hyperparam.find(&amp;quot;__&amp;quot;) + 2:], &amp;quot;: &amp;quot;, gs_rf.best_params_[hyperparam])
        
    print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[94m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;Best 10-folds CV f1-score: {:.2f}%.&amp;quot;.format((gs_rf.best_score_) * 100))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/rf_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/rf_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Random Forest hyperparameter tuning results.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Upsampling yielded the highest CV f1-score with 99.8%. Therefore, we’ll be using the upsampled data to fit the rest of the classifiers. The new data now has 18,284 examples: 50% belonging to the positive class, and 50% belonging to the negative class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s refit the Random Forest with Upsampled data using best hyperparameters tuned above and plot confusion matrix and ROC curve using test data.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/rf_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/rf_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Random Forest.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 1.5em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Gradient Boosting Trees
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gradient Boosting trees are the same as Random Forest except for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It starts with small tree and start learning from grown trees by taking into account the residual of grown trees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More trees can lead to overfitting; opposite to Random Forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can think of each tree as a weak learner. The two other hyperparameters than &lt;code&gt;max_features&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n_estimators&lt;/code&gt; that we&#39;re going to tune are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;learning_rate&lt;/code&gt;: rate the tree learns, the slower the better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;max_depth&lt;/code&gt;: number of split each time a tree is growing which limits the number of nodes in each tree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s fit GB classifier and plot confusion matrix and ROC curve using test data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build Gradient Boosting classifier
pip_gb = make_pipeline(StandardScaler(),
                       GradientBoostingClassifier(loss=&amp;quot;deviance&amp;quot;,
                                                  random_state=123))
hyperparam_grid = {&amp;quot;gradientboostingclassifier__max_features&amp;quot;: [&amp;quot;log2&amp;quot;, 0.5],
                   &amp;quot;gradientboostingclassifier__n_estimators&amp;quot;: [100, 300, 500],
                   &amp;quot;gradientboostingclassifier__learning_rate&amp;quot;: [0.001, 0.01, 0.1],
                   &amp;quot;gradientboostingclassifier__max_depth&amp;quot;: [1, 2, 3]}
gs_gb = GridSearchCV(pip_gb,
                      param_grid=hyperparam_grid,
                      scoring=&amp;quot;f1&amp;quot;,
                      cv=10,
                      n_jobs=-1)
gs_gb.fit(X_train, y_train)
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[0m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;The best hyperparameters:&amp;quot;)
print(&amp;quot;-&amp;quot; * 25)
for hyperparam in gs_gb.best_params_.keys():
    print(hyperparam[hyperparam.find(&amp;quot;__&amp;quot;) + 2:], &amp;quot;: &amp;quot;, gs_gb.best_params_[hyperparam])
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[94m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;Best 10-folds CV f1-score: {:.2f}%.&amp;quot;.format((gs_gb.best_score_) * 100))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/gb_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/gb_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Gradient Boosting Trees hyperparameter tuning results.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;





  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/gb_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/gb_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Gradient Boosting Trees.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 1.5em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
K-Nearest Neighbors
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KNN is called a lazy learning algorithm because it doesn’t learn or fit any parameter. It takes &lt;code&gt;n_neighbors&lt;/code&gt; points from the training data closest to the point we&#39;re interested to predict it&#39;s class and take the mode (majority vote) of the classes for the neighboring point as its class. The two hyperparameters we&#39;re going to tune are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;n_neighbors&lt;/code&gt;: number of neighbors to use in prediction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weights&lt;/code&gt;: how much weight to assign neighbors based on:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“uniform”: all neighboring points have the same weight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“distance”: use the inverse of euclidean distance of each neighboring point used in prediction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s fit KNN classifier and plot confusion matrix and ROC curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build KNN classifier
pip_knn = make_pipeline(StandardScaler(), KNeighborsClassifier())
hyperparam_range = range(1, 20)
gs_knn = GridSearchCV(pip_knn,
                      param_grid={&amp;quot;kneighborsclassifier__n_neighbors&amp;quot;: hyperparam_range,
                                  &amp;quot;kneighborsclassifier__weights&amp;quot;: [&amp;quot;uniform&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;distance&amp;quot;]},
                      scoring=&amp;quot;f1&amp;quot;,
                      cv=10,
                      n_jobs=-1)
gs_knn.fit(X_train, y_train)
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[0m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;The best hyperparameters:&amp;quot;)
print(&amp;quot;-&amp;quot; * 25)
for hyperparam in gs_knn.best_params_.keys():
    print(hyperparam[hyperparam.find(&amp;quot;__&amp;quot;) + 2:], &amp;quot;: &amp;quot;, gs_knn.best_params_[hyperparam])
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[94m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;Best 10-folds CV f1-score: {:.2f}%.&amp;quot;.format((gs_knn.best_score_) * 100))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/knn_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/knn_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;K-Nearest Neighbors hyperparameter tuning results.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;





  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/knn_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/knn_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;K-Nearest Neighbors.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 1.5em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Logistic Regression
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For logistic regression, we’ll tune three hyperparameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;penalty&lt;/code&gt;: type of regularization, L2 or L1 regularization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;: the opposite of regularization of parameter λλ. The higher C the less regularization. We&#39;ll use values that cover the full range between unregularized to fully regularized where model is the mode of the examples&#39; label.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;fit_intercept&lt;/code&gt;: whether to include intercept or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We won’t use any non-linearities such as polynomial features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build logistic model classifier
pip_logmod = make_pipeline(StandardScaler(),
                           LogisticRegression(class_weight=&amp;quot;balanced&amp;quot;))
hyperparam_range = np.arange(0.5, 20.1, 0.5)
hyperparam_grid = {&amp;quot;logisticregression__penalty&amp;quot;: [&amp;quot;l1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;l2&amp;quot;],
                   &amp;quot;logisticregression__C&amp;quot;:  hyperparam_range,
                   &amp;quot;logisticregression__fit_intercept&amp;quot;: [True, False]
                  }
gs_logmodel = GridSearchCV(pip_logmod,
                           hyperparam_grid,
                           scoring=&amp;quot;accuracy&amp;quot;,
                           cv=2,
                           n_jobs=-1)
gs_logmodel.fit(X_train, y_train)
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[0m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;The best hyperparameters:&amp;quot;)
print(&amp;quot;-&amp;quot; * 25)
for hyperparam in gs_logmodel.best_params_.keys():
    print(hyperparam[hyperparam.find(&amp;quot;__&amp;quot;) + 2:], &amp;quot;: &amp;quot;, gs_logmodel.best_params_[hyperparam])
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[94m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;Best 10-folds CV f1-score: {:.2f}%.&amp;quot;.format((gs_logmodel.best_score_) * 100))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/logmodel_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/logmodel_hyperparam.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Logistic Regression hyperparameter tuning results.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;





  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/logmodel_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/logmodel_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Logistic Regression.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 1.5em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Support Vector Machine
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVM is comutationally very expensive to tune it’s hyperparameters for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With big datasets, it becomes very slow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has good number of hyperparameters to tune that takes very long time to tune on a CPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we’ll use recommended hyperparameters’ values from the paper we mentioned before that showed to yield the best performane on Penn Machine Learning Benchmark 165 datasets. The hyperparameters that we usually look to tune are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C, gamma, kernel, degree&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;coef0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Build SVM classifier
clf_svc = make_pipeline(StandardScaler(),
                        SVC(C=0.01,
                            gamma=0.1,
                            kernel=&amp;quot;poly&amp;quot;,
                            degree=5,
                            coef0=10,
                            probability=True))
clf_svc.fit(X_train, y_train)
svc_cv_scores = cross_val_score(clf_svc,
                                X=X_train,
                                y=y_train,
                                scoring=&amp;quot;f1&amp;quot;,
                                cv=10,
                                n_jobs=-1)
# Print CV
print(&amp;quot;\033[1m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;\033[94m&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;The 10-folds CV f1-score is: {:.2f}%&amp;quot;.format(
       np.mean(svc_cv_scores) * 100))
The 10-folds CV f1-score is: 96.38%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 10-folds CV f1-score is: 96.38%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/svc_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/svc_roc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Support Vector Machine.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 style=&#34;font-family: Georgia; font-size: 2em; color:purple; font-style:bold&#34;&gt;
Conclusion
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s conclude by printing out the test accuracy rates for all classifiers we’ve trained so far and plot ROC curves. Then we will pick the classifier that has the highest area under ROC curve.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/overall.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/overall.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Comparing ROC curves for all classifiers.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even though Random Forest and Gradient Boosting Trees have almost equal AUC, Random Forest has higher accuracy rate and an f1-score with 99.27% and 99.44% respectively. Therefore, we safely say Random Forest outperforms the rest of the classifiers. Let’s have a look of feature importances from Random Forest classifier.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/feature_importance.PNG&#34; &gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://imaddabbura.github.io/img/employee-turnover/feature_importance.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Random Forest feature importance.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looks like the five most important features are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;satisfaction_level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time_spend_company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;average_montly_hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number_project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lats_evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The take home message is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When dealing with imbalanced classes, accuracy is not a good method for model evaluation. AUC and f1-score are examples of metrics we can use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upsampling/downsampling, data synthetic and using balanced class weights are good strategies to try to improve the accuracy of a classifier for imbalanced classes datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;GridSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; helps tune hyperparameters for each learning algorithm. &lt;code&gt;RandomizedSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; is faster and may outperform &lt;code&gt;GridSearchCV&lt;/code&gt; especially when we have more than two hyperparameters to tune.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principal Component Analysis (PCA) isn’t always recommended especially if the data is in a good feature space and their eigen values are very close to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As expected, ensemble models outperforms other learning algorithms in most cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
